So far we have talked about confidence intervals with population variances that are either known or
unknown.
However we were considering only one population in the next couple of lessons.
We will explore confidence intervals looking into two populations.
These cases are more important as they have a wide range of real world applications.
A few important distinctions need to be made.
Before we dive into this topic in some cases the samples that we have taken from the two populations
will be dependent on each other and in others they will be independent dependent.
Samples are easier you will experience this firsthand when we have independent samples however we can
further distinguish three cases when the population variance is known when the population variance is
unknown but assumed to be equal.
And when it is unknown and assumed to be different sounds a bit overwhelming.
But don't worry in statistics many concepts are similar to each other and you will quickly see that
you have already acquired the intuition that allows you to understand these concepts pretty fast.
All right let's get onto the first case namely dependent samples.
This statistical test is often used when developing medicine.
Let's say you have developed a pill that increases the concentration of magnesium in the blood.
It is very promising but there is no data to support your claim.
After testing the drug in the laboratory it is time to see its actual effect on people.
What you would typically do is take a sample of 10 people and test their magnesium levels before and
after taking the pill.
The two dependent samples are the magnesium levels before and the magnesium levels after it is clear
that it is the same people we are testing.
Thus the samples are dependent an important note is that the populations are normally distributed actually
when dealing with biology.
Normality is so often observed that we immediately assume that such variables are normally distributed
OK back to the example.
Whenever you take a blood test the magnesium levels are stated in milligrams per deciliter and a healthy
person would usually have somewhere between 1.7 and 2.2 milligrams of magnesium per deciliter.
Here is a table that contains the sample of 10 people and their levels of magnesium before and after
taking the pill for some time.
We've also added a cell that calculates the difference in levels before and after taking the pill instead
of dealing with two variables.
We now have only one in this way.
The data looks as a single population doesn't it.
Let's calculate the mean and the standard deviation of the differences the mean is zero point three
three.
And the standard deviation is zero point four or five.
Moreover we know that the sample size is 10.
The formula that would allow us to calculate a confidence interval is the following.
The population is normally distributed but the sample we have contains only 10 observations.
Therefore the distribution will have to work with students T and the appropriate statistic is t.
You can clearly see that it is the same as the one for a single population with an unknown variance.
Let's choose a level of confidence and plug in the numbers as we have said many times.
95 percent confidence is one of the most common levels.
And so we will use it here as well.
The t statistic with nine degrees of freedom for a 95 percent confidence interval is 2.2 6.
Now we have everything we need and we can calculate the confidence interval.
It lies in the range between 0.01 and 0.6 5.
How do we interpret this result.
Well 95 percent of the cases the true mean will fall in this interval.
Moreover the whole interval is positive.
This shows that the true meaning of the difference is definitely positive.
Therefore with 95 percent certainty we can say that the levels of magnesium in the test subjects blood
is higher.
The purpose of this test was to determine whether the drug is effective based on our small sample.
It most likely is.
All right.
This shows you some of the practical applications of inference.
Stay tuned for our next lesson in which we will explore confidence intervals on independence Serviles.