In our last video we learned about confidence intervals for two means based on dependent samples.
In this video we will explore independent samples as we said earlier.
There are three sub cases known population variances unknown population variances but assumed to be
equal an unknown population variances that are assumed to be different.
Here we will focus on independent samples with known population variances.
All right let's jump right into the example that would allow us to understand the concept a bit better.
We would like to get the test grades of two departments in a UK university.
University grades in the UK expressed in percentages.
Our samples are taken from two departments engineering and management.
The table you see here summarizes the data.
We have a sample of 100 engineering students and the average grade is 58 percent.
From past years we know that the population standard deviation is 10 percentage points.
Thus the variance is known.
We also have a sample of 70 students from the management department and we've got a sample mean of 65
percent.
Again from past data we know that the population standard deviation is 5 percent OK.
But before we get on with calculations.
Let's point out three important considerations.
First the populations are normally distributed.
Second the population variances are known and third the sample sizes are different.
Different sample sizes are a common occurrence in the real world in our previous lesson.
When we had dependent samples we were testing the same people over time so it made sense that the sample
sizes were equally big.
This time however the observations are completely different.
They are students from different departments with different teachers obtaining different grades when
taking different exams.
The great of a person from engineering doesn't in any way affect the grade of a person studying management
right.
The two samples are truly independent.
All right.
What are we testing.
We want to find a 95 percent confidence interval for the difference between the grades of the students
from engineering and management as with every confidence interval.
We must identify the test to take samples.
Our big population variances are known and populations are assumed to follow the normal distribution.
All this information points us to the Z statistic instead of the T.
The last ingredient is the variance.
We haven't been through enough mathematics in this course to derive the formula so we will simply state
it.
The variance of the difference between the two means is equal to the variance of the grades received
by engineering students divided by the sample size of engineering students plus the variance of grades
obtained by management students divided by the sample size of management students the underlying logic
is that dispersion is additive.
More variables means higher or equal variability.
OK so what is the confidence interval formula this time well it is given by the expression below.
X bar minus Y Bar is the difference point estimator Z is the statistic.
And this is the variance of the difference.
We plug in the numbers and get a confidence interval between minus nine point to 8 and minus 4.7 to.
All right what's the interpretation.
We are 95 percent confident that the true mean difference between engineering and management grades
falls into this interval.
Note that this time the whole interval is negative.
This is because we were calculating engineering grade minus management grade as the engineers were consistently
getting lower grades.
The difference is negative.
Had we calculated the difference as management minus engineering we would have obtained a confidence
interval between 4.7 to and nine point to eight completely symmetrical around zero.
All right great.
Remember to do all the exercises available in the course materials as the topics are getting tougher
and tougher.
See you next time.
And thanks for watching.