Finally it's time for the practical example we've been talking about in this lesson we will see an actual
database of a real estate company operating in California.
All right we're interested in the statistical properties of the data.
That is why we have reordered the database and cherry picked variable than imported DS in a spreadsheet.
The labels of the columns have been made friendly even for those of you who have no experience with
real estate.
Finally we have altered the names of the customers for confidentiality reasons.
OK.
The company is launching a marketing campaign but it wants to target its audience properly.
The management suspects after some shore analysis marketing results can be improved without the need
of investing additional resources.
We are the data analysis who are going to crunch some numbers and identify which groups of people are
most likely to buy our product.
Once we have done so we will instruct the marketing team to focus its efforts on these groups.
The first thing we have to do when we analyze data is get acquainted with the table.
It illustrates the skills of real estate property for a specific company.
Lets call it 365 data sites real estate Calif..
Hopefully no one else thought of that name.
Second the table has two parts left and right on the left hand side.
We have product information on the right hand side.
We have customer information.
You can easily spot all products are listed but customer information is only available for some products.
This is because we input information about a customer once the deal is done logically only sold items
are associated with a buyer.
Lets see what a roll looks like.
This should clear up the logic of the table for you Nora Lynch with a customer id see 0 0 0 4 was 56
years old when she bought a apartment 43 in building one to live there.
She paid three hundred seventy seven thousand three hundred thirteen dollars for an area of 1000 160
square feet.
In June 2004 Nora is from California.
Felt very satisfied with the deal and did not get a mortgage for the purchase.
She found out about our product through our website.
Okay now that that's out of the way we need to dig deeper into these variables.
We will identify types of data and levels of measurement for some of them.
This is a crucial step as we cannot analyze the data.
If we don't understand its type.
Lets start from the first column ID.
ID is a value we assign to each item that lets us differentiate between products.
It may look numerical to you but it is categorical that's counter-intuitive the first time.
So let's clarify it.
What if we use names like John John to John 3 and so on until John N.
The meaning would not change id variables are like names we assign to different products.
However it is much easier to use numbers as unlike names we have an infinite number of numbers.
A simple way to check if a variable is numerical or categorical is to interpret its mean.
Think about it.
The mean ID number shows nothing.
Now oppose this to the mean price.
The mean price is a valuable piece of information.
OK the bottom line is ID is a categorical variable.
What about its level of measurement.
Well it is qualitative nominal.
Clear.
The next variable we must examine is age.
Age is rather interesting.
The level of measurement is quantitative ratio.
A rule used for verifying ratios is asking the question.
Is there a true zero point.
Well for age when you are born you are exactly zero years old.
That's the true zero point.
So we are safe.
However once intriguing is whether age is discrete or continuous It may be both.
In this case we can only see age as a whole number.
Therefore it is discrete.
However similar to weight of variable we discussed earlier in this course.
Age is a continuous variable.
When I am recording this the Statue of Liberty is 131 years old but I may get more specific by saying
it is 131 years and 11 months old or its age is 131 92.
If I had days minutes and seconds I'll get 131 nine thousand four hundred twelve.
You get the point when dealing with age.
You decide it's time depending on your work at hand.
The next variable we have is age interval.
This is yet another way to represent age.
Once again it is continuous or discrete as we are talking about the same variable This time though the
level of measurement is ordinal instead of a ratio the age groups represent different categories ordered
but are not numerical.
This shows that the same variable can have different levels of measurement within the same database.
All right let's move on.
In most corporate analysis price is Central no matter the data set it is always a numerical variable
that like age may be discrete or continuous depending on your needs.
If you are interested banks and corporations treat it as continuous and so will we.
The level of measurement here is ratio.
The next variable we want to look into is gender.
It is of categorical type and its level of measurement is nominal.
It is similar to the yes no questions discussed in a previous lesson.
Such variables are called binary as there are only two possibilities.
Finally let's check out the location.
We will discuss state in more detail and leave country for homework.
The state variable refers to sales in the USA only.
Note that only if the country input is USA.
Would we have a value for state.
State is a categorical variable like ID.
We talked about earlier.
You can label the US states from 1 to 50 and news numbers instead.
Either way the variable is categorical and its level of measurement is nominal.
OK excellent.
We've categorized the variables we will use in this video.
This spreadsheet is available for you in the resources section with the exercises we've prepared on
this database.
You can practice the entire section about descriptive statistics.
All right back to our problem at hand we must identify the groups of people who buy the most of our
product.
Let's start with gender before we can plot the data.
We must create the frequency distribution table in the course notes.
You can see how that's done in Excel.
However in this video I'll skip this step and get to the frequency distribution table.
Now we have three possibilities for gender male female or a cell where gender is not available.
Since some properties were purchased by companies they have no gender.
We have to include them in the analysis or explain why we omitted in the report.
Gender is categorical.
We said that a good way to represent it in practice is with a pie chart.
OK we can clearly see most clients are male.
However this information is biased as the customers in this database are the people who signed the contract.
It is likely a family bought the apartment but our data shows us only the person who signed the contract.
Such variables are interesting to see but it is not a good idea to include them in the data driven decisions
we make.
OK let's carry on with location.
What chart would be useful to show this state is a categorical variable.
We may use a bar chart or a pie chart.
However I prefer the Pareto diagram as it gives additional information from the graph.
You can immediately see.
Most clients are from California.
A possible scenario is to invest in marketing for the Top 75 percent of the locations.
This will mean we can focus on California and Nevada alone.
Next we want to see age.
First we have to note that age represents the age of the buyer when the deal was sealed.
The formula used is the year of the deal minus the year of the birth of the buyer.
We are doing this because we want to see the age at which customers buy our product.
Their current age is irrelevant.
Real estate is something people rarely buy more than once in their life.
So age will probably be a central variable in our analysis.
Let's first Plup the frequency distribution of age this is done by creating a histogram with an interval
length of one.
Now we can move on to the age interval representation.
The options are 18 to 25 26 to 35 36 to 45 56 to 65 and 65 plus most of the data falls between 25 and
60 years which is evident from the frequency distribution graph.
Therefore our intervals are a good fit of the data.
Let's build a new histogram based on them done.
This representation is much neater isn't it.
We can clearly see 36 to 45 is the age at which most people purchase a real estate property.
It is evident that customers from 26 to 65 years old account for 71 percent of our observations.
But we are better than this.
We can calculate more statistics to get an improved idea can't we.
Let's do it.
The mean median and mode are the place where we usually start the mean age is forty six point fifteen
years the median age is 45 years and the mode is 48 years.
All right.
The mean and median are close.
So we have few outliers as you may recall.
The mean is affected by them while the median is not when the mean is higher than the median.
We have a positive or right skew.
This is confirmed by our histogram.
Now is the time to remind you that skewness shows too which side is the longer tail not where the data
is concentrated.
Now for the mode we have 48 years you can see that from the frequency distribution graph but not from
the histogram.
The histogram bundles data together which is good when we want to see the main trend but some information
like the mode is lost.
Finally we should inspect the variability of age before we can do so.
We have to see if this is sample or population data.
The company data is the population of all people who are our customers.
However our research aims to help the marketing department identify future customers.
Therefore our dataset is a sample drawn from all the people who will eventually buy property from our
company.
Henceforth we will use sample formulas.
Let's compute both the variance and the standard deviation.
The former is measured in squared years and the latter in years.
So I suggest we stick with the standard deviation then shall we.
The result is around 13 years.
This shows us how dispersed the data is.
What inferences can we make from this result.
Well that's the topic of the next section so we all have to halt here.
As you may have guessed our final stop is relationship between variables.
Let's see if age determines how expensive an apartment that customers buy.
Maybe younger people have less funds so they buy cheaper apartments.
We don't know the data will tell us first things first.
Let's plop the data both variables are numerical so we must use a scatter plot.
Here it is.
It is dispersed and there isn't an obvious trend.
Let's confirm this observation by calculating the covariance of the two variables.
We get this enormous value that doesn't tell us much.
So it's suitable to standardize it by using the correlation coefficient.
The value we get is minus 0.17 much better.
This correlation is low.
A common practice is to disregard correlations that are below zero point to Alright.
So real estate expenditure is not related to age from a previous lesson.
We know price and size are much more likely to be correlated right.
You have all the tools needed to check this through the exercise.
After this lesson so we've exhausted our statistical knowledge what can we tell the marketing team after
this short analysis.
Well we got several insights.
First males are more likely to sign contracts and are potentially a better audience for our ads.
However we have no information about their marital status.
This observation is unclear.
Second 68 percent of our sales in the US come from California with Nevada Oregon Arizona and Colorado
following behind to form 93 percent of the US customer base third 71 percent of sales were made with
customers aged between 26 and 55 years old with a mean of 46 years of age and a standard deviation of
13 years.
The distribution is right skewed so we expect younger people to buy more property than older people.
Finally there is no relationship between the age of a customer and the price they will pay.
All right that was our practical example.
We learned a lot about this business but we could not get amazing insights in the following sections.
We will learn about confidence intervals and hypothesis testing.
This knowledge will provide us with the tools we need to make predictions about the future and make
data driven decisions.
Oh and one more thing if you like the course so far.
Please leave us a review.
It helps a lot.
Thanks for practicing and thanks for watching.