Hello and welcome to our third practical example this time we will explore the topic of gender pay gap.
We will test whether a particular company is discriminating against some of its employees on a gender
basis.
Our fictitious company is called Sparke fortress incorporated.
It is a big company with more than 5000 employees.
And here we will work with a sample of one hundred seventy four of them.
We have data showing us their name age gender nationality ethnicity tenure Department position and annual
salary.
I believe there is no need for further explanation of the data set.
We are going to test if there is a significant difference in the salaries.
Employees are paid based on their gender.
It would be easier if we looked at the problem at hand.
In the following way our 174 employees sample can be divided into two sub samples one that is exclusively
male and one female.
So we have two samples drawn from the same population which are independent although so far we've worked
with different populations only if the values in one sample reveal no information about the other sample
then they are considered independent.
There are different methodologies to conduct such a study and while regression analysis is my preferred
one we will have to wait until the next section for that here.
We will use a hypothesis test for the mean salary to determine if there is reasonable evidence of gender
discrimination let's state the two hypotheses age zero.
The average male salary is equal to the average female salary or myu F-minus me f equal zero H-1 the
average male salary differs from the average female salary OK.
The test we should use is the t test for independent samples.
What about the salary population variance.
It is a known and we can assume it has equal let's construct a frequency distribution table.
We have 98 females and 76 males.
These are our sample sizes.
Next we should calculate the means and the sample variances of the two samples that we have as we assume
that the population variances are equal.
We should also compute the pooled variance.
Here's the good old formula and here's the ginormous results.
Finally the score for this test is computed following the familiar expression.
We get a score of 1.3 for the degrees of freedom are one hundred seventy two as we said earlier.
Once we have surpassed 50 degrees of freedom the Student's t distribution almost completely overlaps
with the normal distribution.
Thus the p values for a score of 1.3 for an a z score of 1.3 for will be virtually the same you already
know how to use a p value calculator.
So I'll just give you the p value.
It's 0.1 8 to the p value is much greater than all common levels of significance.
We conclude that we cannot reject the null hypothesis.
There isn't enough statistical evidence that there is a wage gap in this firm.
Now that's cool.
Sparke fortress seems like a nice place to work at.
But let's dig just a bit deeper into this result.
Personally I'd be interested to know if there is no wage gap at all.
Or maybe there is one hidden beneath the aggregate values we just investigated.
Sometimes it is a good idea to examine the data set manually.
That's something we didn't do in the beginning but we should have done let's order the salaries from
largest to the smallest we can see that the highest paid employee is actually the president and CEO
of the company.
Caroline bulled who is female.
This may explain the gelateria and culture of the company but it may also mean that her high salary
biased our data.
What if on average it seems that women are rewarded the same as men but in fact very few of them are
in such cases.
I would normally further segment the data lets divide the employees into two more groups below 35 and
above 35.
This will give us valuable information about the wage equality of younger and older staff.
I've created two more data sets that are based on the original one.
Let's run the same tests as before but this time we will do it on our segmented data.
The hypotheses are the same.
What we get for these two tests is a score of 0.4 3 for employees below 35 and 2.00 for employees over
35.
The corresponding p values are 0.6 x 8 and zero point zero for eight.
What these numbers mean is that in the group below 35 there is virtually no wage gap on a gender basis.
The p value is so big that we made sure there is no discrimination going on in the older group however
the p value is zero point zero for eight.
This is very close to 0.05 but still below it.
This implies that at a 95 percent significance we reject the null hypothesis.
Therefore a wage gap does exist for older employees.
All right.
This was a two sided test.
So we are not sure who gets more money right.
Well do you remember the nifty trick the score of 2 is positive.
Therefore the difference in pay is positive in favor of males.
A limitation for this analysis is that we omitted other factors such as position and ethnicity.
So we are not completely sure what's going on in the firm but we can say that overall there is no wage
gap and Sparke fortress.
And this is driven by wage equality among young employees.
This is a good indicator as it means that the company is firmly moving towards complete equality.
All right.
Your homework is to conduct a similar test that aims to capture if there is racial discrimination in
the firm.
You can find the data in the resources for this lesson.
Good luck and thanks for watching.