Hey if this section seems too theoretical now is the time to prove you wrong.
We will deal with a real life example about car sales.
Actually it is so real life that it is very messy and we will need to first clean our dataset then go
through several assumptions relax them on them.
Practice with the concept of log transformation.
We mentioned earlier create a model and we will eventually finish off with some dummy variables.
I bet you will be blown away by all the things you already know everything will be interconnected.
So get comfortable and let's start analyzing heres our data set.
This is a list of second hand cars with their respective price type of body mileage engine volume engine
type year of production and model.
What we would like to do is predict the price of a used car depending on its specifications.
The first potential aggressor is brand as it is well known that a BMW is generally more expensive than
a Toyota.
The second relevant variable is mileage since the car is driven the cheaper it should be.
Third the engine volume sports cars have larger engines and economy cars have smaller engines and the
final variable is year of production.
The older the car the cheaper it is with the exception of vintage vehicles.
These are the variables we will focus on.
All right.
We haven't spoken about data cleaning so far in this course.
Our focus was statistics.
So I was always cleaning the data sets for you before presenting them.
This time it will be different and you will get a feeling of what raw data looks like.
I will go column by column.
Excel is not optimized for data analysis but it has sufficient resources for our current needs.
An easy way to spot problems with your data in Excel such as missing values is to sort the cells.
So I'll start sorting the relevant cells brand looks fine.
Price however has lots of missing values.
There are different methodologies for sorting this out but I will simply remove all observations that
do not include a price as price is the dependent variable.
It is a big issue in our analysis.
If there is no price listed a rule of thumb is that if you are removing less than 5 percent of the observations
you are free to just remove all observations that have missing values.
In this case they are 4.4 percent.
The next variable is mileage and thousands of miles there are missing values for it as well.
We are not sure if these are zeros or something else looking at the year of production and the price
they most likely are.
While more diligence should be applied.
I'll just add zeros here.
The next variable is the engine.
We can see many values that are not available.
It's best to delete these variables OK but then there are also the engine volume values of ninety nine
point ninety nine ninety seventy five etc..
I am no car expert but these are not usual values.
Moreover looking through all 4000 plus values we noticed that most entries are in the range from 0.6
to 6.5.
A quick search on Google would confirm that's the interval where engine volume should fall.
Therefore those ninety nine point ninety nine 90s and so on are incorrect entries actually a common
way to label missing values is by assigning ninety nine point ninety nine.
That's something that's stuck from the early ages of computers.
It is a bad idea to label values in such ways as it is very hard for other users of the data to distinguish
them from the true values.
However be aware that some people still do it.
Let's remove these entries.
The last value of interest is the year when a car was produced.
There are no problems with it.
We're good to go.
All right so far we have identified brand mileage engine volume and year of production as regressors
brand is categorical data.
Linearity is not going to be an issue there as the brand will be included in the regression through
dummy variables.
We are left with price mileage and year where price is the dependent variable of the regression.
Let's check for linearity using a scatterplot.
These are the three scatter plots that we obtain one for a price and mileage one for price and year
and one for price and engine volume.
We can spot patterns but definitely not linear ones projected by Excel with the orange trend line.
We know we should not run a linear regression in this case.
We should first transform one or more variables as I have told you before log transformation is a common
way of dealing with this issue.
It is especially useful when facing exponential scatterplot like we do now.
Let's take the log of prices and plot them again.
All right.
We can see a linear pattern in the plots.
Now the lines fit the data so much better.
However I'd like to take the log of mileage and do a log log scatterplot as I suspect that we will get
even better results.
Ok I was kind of wrong.
It is hard to say if this is an improvement but let's keep the log of mileage in the regression as to
see how is a log log relationship interpreted superb.
Next we have to deal with the no endogenous assumption.
There are tests to check if it is violated or one can take the residuals and find their correlation
with each independent x.
I can tell you that the assumption is not violated.
So it is of no interest.
The third assumption had several parts.
Normality is assumed for a big sample following the Central Limit Theorem.
The zero mean of the distribution of errors is accomplished through the inclusions of the intercept
in the regression finally the homeless get STC the assumption generally holds as we can see in the graphs.
The reason for that is that we already implemented a log transformation which is the most common fix
for hetero's cadets Tisci.
The fourth assumption is no autocorrelation.
We don't really need to put much effort into that.
The observations we have are not coming from time series data or Pennel data.
They are simply a snapshot of the current situation at a second hand car sales website.
Each row comes from a different customer who is willing to sell their car through the platform.
Logically there is no reason for the observations to be dependent on each other.
We are safe.
Finally we should check for multi-collinearity that can be done by finding the correlations of all possible
pairs of variables mileage with your mileage with engine volume and year with engine volume.
The correlations are far from strong so we can conclude that we are not in the presence of multi-collinearity.
After having checked the assumptions we can finally create the regression.
First let's explain the log price with log mileage.
OK we can see that the model is significant.
The explanatory variable is significant too and the R-squared of the regression is 0.27.
So we have some explanatory power but this is not a very powerful model.
Similarily.
The R-squared of a regression of price with engine volume is zero point to one next let's explain log
price with year both the model and the variable are significant the R-Squared is 0.5 6 so year explains
56 percent of the variability of a car's price.
That's a remarkable relationship.
Now let's create a regression using all three variables mileage year and engine volume.
The model and all variables are significant.
We already expected that given that we created three regressions earlier.
However this time the adjusted R-squared is 0.7 7 therefore the three variables together explain 77
percent of the total variability.
That's a very nice and rigid model already to conclude the example we would like to include the brand
in the regression.
There are seven brands Audi BMW Mercedes Mitsubishi Renault Toyota and Volkswagen.
This is categorical data.
In order to be included in the regression we have to create dummy variables already dummy would be one
if the brand is Audi and 0 if it is not BMW dummy would be one if the brand is BMW and 0 if it is not.
And so on for the last brand.
In this case Volkswagen we will not create a dummy variable.
The reasoning is the following.
If all other dummy variables are 0 it is clear that the car is Volkswagen if we include a separate variable
called Volkswagen.
We will introduce multi-collinearity to the regression the Volkswagen dummy would be perfectly determined
by the other variables.
Thus if we have any categories there will be only and minus one dummys.
We are basically creating the dummy variables as we did in our previous lesson.
Now let's run a new regression including the dummys the final model that we get is significant.
Moreover each variable included is significant.
The adjusted R-squared of the model is 0.8.
This regression has a very high explanatory power.
The only thing we have left is to interpret the result.
The model is the log of price equals minus seventy eight point four one plus minus 0.1 one times log
of mileage plus 0.1 four times the engine volume plus zero point zero four times the year of the car
plus the dummys.
Let's look at them one by one.
Keep in mind that our dependent variable is the logarithm of the price.
So the interpretation will be a bit different than usual
the intercept is clear mileage the log of price changes by minus 0.1 one times log of mileage.
As I told you in one of our previous lessons this can be interpreted in the following way for each percentage
change in mileage the price decreases by 0.1 1 percent.
Engine volume.
The interpretation is the following for each extra unit or leader of engine volume the logarithm of
price increases by 0.1 4 to see the impact on price.
We have to get back to the original variable the same way multiplying and dividing are opposite operations
taking the exponential and taking the log R2.
There are further explanations in the course notes but bear with me log price changes by 0.1 for normal
price is equal to E to the power of log price.
So to get the change in price we should find the exponential of 0.1 for therefore the price would change
to 1.1 5 of its original value.
That is a 1.1 5 minus 1 percent increase or 15 percent.
Once again please check the course notes if you need clarification of the math involved.
Year of production for each additional year the price increase is by the exponential of 0.04 minus 1
in percentages.
That is 4 percent.
Finally we have the dummys we have 6 dummys Audi BMW Mercedes Mitsubishi Renault and Toyota.
We have included Volkswagen as we said that the dummy should be one less than the options.
So if all dummies are know then we get this model Another fact is that if all dumpings are no then the
car is not.
Audi BMW Mercedes Mitsubishi Renault or Toyota.
It is a Volkswagen.
So actually the dummies give us a comparison with the Volkswagen car.
That's the benchmark
the coefficient of the Audi dummy is 0.06.
Therefore all else being equal the price of an Audi is 6 percent higher than a Volkswagen price Similarily
the prices of a BMW and Mercedes are 12 percent and 11 percent more than that of a Volkswagen Mitsubishi
is 5 percent cheaper in a Renault is the cheapest at a 17 percent lower price.
To exhaust the dummys all else equal a Toyota is 4 percent more expensive than a Volkswagen.
All right.
This wraps up our exercise on regression analysis.
This was my favorite topic so far and I hope you had fun.
See you next time.
And thanks for watching.