Before we can talk about testing we have to learn what a distribution is.
And in this lesson we'll do just that in statistics when we use the term distribution we usually mean
a probability distribution.
Good examples are the normal distribution the binomial distribution and the uniform distribution.
All right let's start with a definition.
A distribution is a function that shows the possible values for a variable and how often they occur.
Think about Addai it has 6 sides numbered from 1 to 6.
We roll the die.
What is the probability of getting one.
It is 1 out of 6.
So 1 6 3.
What is the probability of getting 2.
Once again one sixth.
The same holds for 3 4 5 and 6.
Now what is the probability of getting a 7.
It is impossible to get a 7 when rolling a die.
Therefore the probability is zero.
The distribution of an event consists not only of the input values that can be observed but is made
up of all the possible values.
So the distribution of the event rolling a die will be given by the following table.
The probability of getting 1 is 0.17 the probability of getting 2 is 0.17 and so on.
You are sure that you have exhausted all possible values when the sum of the probabilities is equal
to 100 percent for all other values.
The probability of occurrence is zero.
Each probability distribution is associated with a graph describing the likelihood of occurrence of
every event.
Here's the graph for our example.
This type of distribution is called uniform distribution.
It is crucial to understand that the distribution is defined by the underlying probabilities and not
the graph.
The graph is just a visual representation.
All right.
Now think about rolling two dice.
What are the possibilities 1 and 1 2 and 1 1 and 2 and so on.
Here's a table with all the possible combinations.
We are interested in the sum of two dice.
So what's the probability of getting a sum of 1 0 as this event is impossible.
What's the probability of getting a sum of two.
There is only one combination that would give us the sum of two when both dice are equal to 1.
So 1 out of 36 total outcomes or zero point zero or three Similarily the probability of getting a sum
of three is given by the number of combinations that give a sum of three divided by 36.
Therefore two divided by 36 or 0.06 we continue this way until we have the full probability distribution.
Let's see the graph associated with it.
All right so looking at it we understand that when we roll two dice the probability of getting a seven
is the highest.
We can also compare different outcomes such as the probability of getting a 10 and the probability of
getting a 5.
It's evident that it's less likely that we'll get a 10 grade.
The examples that we saw here were of discrete variables.
Next we will focus on continuous distributions as they are more common in inferences.
In the next few lessons we'll examine some of the main types of continuous distributions starting with
the normal distribution.