OK here we go so far we learned that the distribution of a data set shows us the frequency I wish possible
values occur within an interval.
We also said that there are dozens of distributions experienced statisticians can immediately distinguish
a binomial from a porcelain distribution as well as a uniform from an exponential distribution in a
quick glimpse at a plot in this course though we will rather focus on the normal and students distributions
due to the following reasons they approximate a wide variety of random variables distributions of sample
mean with large enough sample sizes could be approximated to normal all computable statistics are elegant
decisions based on normal distribution insites have a good track record.
If it sounds like gibberish now I promise that things will be much easier once we get started.
Here is a visual representation of a normal distribution.
You have surely seen a normal distribution before as it is the most common one.
The statistical term for it is gone in distribution but many people call it the bell curve as it is
shaped like a bell.
It is symmetrical and its mean median and mode are equal.
If you remember the lesson about skewness you would recognize that it has no skew.
It is perfectly centered around its mean Alright so it is denoted in this way.
N stands for normal.
The tilde assigned denotes it is a distribution and in brackets we have the mean and the variance of
the distribution on the plane.
You can notice that the highest point is located at the mean because it coincides with the mode.
The spread of the graph is determined by the standard deviation.
Now let's try to understand the normal distribution a little bit better.
Let's look at this approximately normal distribution histogram.
There is a concentration of the observations around the mean which makes sense as it is equal to the
mode.
Moreover it is symmetrical on both sides of the mean.
We used 80 observations to create this histogram.
It's mean is 743 and its standard deviation is 140 OK.
Great but what if the mean is smaller or bigger.
Let's zoom out a bit by adding the origin of the graph.
The origin is the zero point.
Adding it to any graph gives perspective.
Keeping the standard deviation fixed or in statistical jargon controlling for the standard deviation
a lower mean would result in the same shape of the distribution.
But on the left side of the plane in the same way a bigger mean would move the graph to the right.
In our example this resulted in two new distributions one with the mean of 470 and a standard deviation
of one hundred forty and one with a mean of 960 and a standard deviation of hundred forty.
All right.
Let's do the opposite controlling for the mean.
We can change the standard deviation and see what happens this time.
The graph is not moving but is rather reshaping a lower standard deviation results in lower dispersion.
So more data in the middle and thinner tails on the other hand a higher standard deviation will cause
the graph to fly now with less points in the middle and more to the end.
Or in statistics jargon fatter tails great.
In our next lesson we will use this knowledge to talk about standardization.
Stay tuned.