The standard normal distribution is a particular case of the normal distribution we'll use the letter
Z to denote it.
It has a mean of zero and a standard deviation of one the standard normal distribution is easy to understand
and has several important applications.
Every normal distribution can be standardized standardization in this context is the process of turning
a normally distributed variable to one with a standard normal distribution.
A simple formula allows us to do that.
The standardized variable the variable whose normal distribution we are turning into a standard normal
distribution is called a z score it is equal to the original variable minus its mean divided by its
standard deviation.
Let's try to interpret it first.
We have to look at the numerator.
If you take a dataset subtract its mean from each data point and then calculate the mean.
Once again you will get zero.
The following example will help us prove that.
Let's take an approximately normally distributed set of numbers 1 2 2 3 3 3 4 4 and 5.
Its mean is 3 and its standard deviation 1.2 2.
Now lets have tracked the mean from all data points.
We get a new dataset of minus two minus 1 minus 1 0 0 0 1 1 and 2.
Let's calculate the mean.
It is 0 exactly as we anticipated.
Clear.
OK great.
So far we have a new distribution which is still normal but with a mean of zero.
Any standard deviation of 1.2 to the next step of standardization is to divide all data points by the
standard deviation.
This will drive the standard deviation of the new data set to 1.
Let's go back to our example.
Both the original data set and the one we obtained after subtracting the mean from each data point have
a standard deviation of 1.2 to remember.
Adding and subtracting to all data points does not change the standard deviation.
Now let's divide each data point by 1.2 to we get minus 1.6 3 minus 0.8 to minus 0.8 to 0 0 0 0.8 to
zero point a two and 1.6 three.
If we calculate the standard deviation of this dataset we will get one and the mean is still zero.
Let's quickly show that cool.
This is how we can obtain a standard normal distribution from any normally distributed data set.
Using it makes predictions and inference much easier.
And this will help us a great deal in what we will see next.
Thanks for watching.