The central limit theorem is one of the most important concepts in statistics.
If you had to choose one thing to remember from this course which I hope you don't we'll see in this
lesson is what you want to remember.
The reason for this is the unmatched practical application of the theorem OK.
Let's get started then imagine that you are given a data set.
Its distribution does not matter.
It could be normal uniform binomial or completely random.
The first thing you want to do is start taking out subsets from the data sets.
Or as statisticians call it you start sampling it.
This would allow you to get a better idea of how the entire data is made.
Right.
OK.
Once you have taken a sufficient number of samples and then calculated the mean of each sample will
be able to apply the Central Limit Theorem.
No matter the distribution of the entire data sets binomial uniform or another one.
The means of the samples you took from the entire dataset will approximate a normal distribution.
The more samples you extract and the bigger they are the closer to a normal distribution the sample
means will be.
Moreover their distribution will have the same mean as the original data set and an end times smaller
variance where n is the size of your samples you took from the data sets.
Let's confirm the theorem with an example.
We have prepared 960 random numbers from 1 to 1000.
This is their frequency distribution.
So you are sure that they are randomly picked the mean of this dataset is 489 and its variance is eighty
two thousand eight hundred five.
Let's extract 30 random samples out of the dataset each consisting of 25 numbers.
Remember when we said that the sample should be sufficiently large.
A common rule of thumb is that the sample should be bigger than 25 observations.
The bigger the sample size the better the results you'll get.
So we have our samples.
Now we are going to calculate their means and plot them once again.
OK.
Excellent.
It looks approximately normally distributed doesn't it.
Let's check if the other part of the theorem was right.
The mean of our newly acquired dataset is 492.
While its variants three thousand one hundred seventy one.
Did we expect these numbers.
We anticipated a mean of four hundred eighty nine and a variance of eighty two thousand eight hundred
five divided by 25.
So around three thousand three hundred twelve well when dealing with such big numbers we almost get
the mean right and the variance was not that far off either in the next few lectures you will learn
how to statistically confirm whether such small differences are close enough to the actual result we
expect to obtain spoiler alert.
They are.
And we'll show you why.
So we have learned the main idea behind the Central Limit Theorem.
The key takeaway from this lesson is that the number of samples taken tends towards infinity the distribution
of the mean start approximating a normal distribution.
Imagine their power if your dataset was made up of millions of values and you could afford to sample
just a tiny bit of them.
We can be assuming normally distributed data almost all the time and that's extremely helpful as you
will see later on OK this will do for now.
Thanks for watching.