With some solid statistical knowledge behind us we are ready to jump into regression analysis which
is arguably the most common method of prediction.
It is used whenever we have a causal relationship between variables for example among other factors.
The money you spend depends on the money you make in the same way the time you devote to this course
depends on your motivation to learn statistics.
We will use our typical systematic approach starting from the simple linear regression model and reaching
the multivariate regression model along the way we will learn how to build a regression how to interpret
it and how to compare different models.
We will develop a deep understanding of the fundamentals as what we'll learn and this section will be
closely related to the knowledge we've acquired so far.
After this section you will be prepared to dive into more advanced statistical analysis or even machine
learning if that's where you want to go.
Brace yourselves.
Regression analysis starts here.