Hi again after we have introduced the topic this lesson will be a lot more quantitative in the first
section of the course.
We talked about correllation.
Remember let's do a quick recap first.
How do we identify a correlation between two variables.
Well one way is to plop them on a scatterplot or a line chart and try to find a pattern.
However as we're getting more acquainted with statistics we would prefer using the correlation coefficient.
Here are the formulas we saw earlier.
All right let's explore a few examples of correlated variables shall we.
Here we have three datasets.
The first one represents the number of movies Vin Diesel makes per year.
The second the U.S. GDP growth rate and the third the UK GDP growth rate.
You can already sense this will be an action packed video.
Let's find the correlation coefficient of these data sets.
I would like to remind you that the correlation coefficients our values from minus 1 to plus one were
zero shows no linear relationship one.
A very strong positive correlation and minus one.
A very strong negative correlation the correlation of Vin Diesel movies and the U.S. GDP growth rate
is 0.4 3.
What's the meaning of this value.
Well a far fetched explanation would be that when times are good and GDP rises Vin Diesel makes more
movies and vice versa.
OK if we calculate the correlation of Vin Diesel movies and the UK GDP growth rate we get 0.4 6.
The number of movies he makes has a stronger correlation with the UK GDP growth.
Although Vinh works in the USA and supposedly has nothing to do with the UK certainly our previous explanation
does not sound convincing.
Finally the correlation of US GDP growth rate and UK GDP growth rate is zero.
Way what's going on.
This doesn't make any sense.
We have to make a few considerations though first does it sound reasonable that gigantic countries like
the USA and the UK will have anything to do with Vin Diesel starring in a film.
Of course not the result we got is pure coincidence.
I assure you that many many things in the world are correlated.
Some even more absurd than our example.
But correlation does not imply causation.
It's easy to find correlations but much harder to find causal relationships to exhaust this example.
We should also comment on the lack of correlation between the US and the UK GDP growth rate.
Well our sample is drawn from the period 2010 to 2015 which is shortly after the US subprime mortgage
crisis and during the European sovereign debt crisis the US and UK were coping with their respective
situations in different ways and the results were mixed.
As you can see the low correlation does not mean one country was doing better than the other.
It shows they are stronger and weaker.
Times were not coinciding in our sample period.
However history tells us that American and European historical growth rates have had a causal relationship
because of trade war and movement of capital and labor.
All right after seeing these three cases what's the bottom line.
Correlation does not imply causation.
This whole lesson was to illustrate that some variables are strangely correlated while others are unexpectedly
uncorrelated in regression analysis.
You will often start with a correlation test to see what's going on with your data.
But be wary as the results could be misleading in the following lessons.
We will get familiar with regressions.
We will take extra time to distinguish between correlation analysis and regression analysis.
All right to conclude.
Let's say it again.
What's the key takeaway from this lesson.
That's right.
Correlation does not imply causation.
Thanks for watching.