Before we go any further what did we say about correlation.
Correlation does not imply causation.
Let's spend one more minute on that first correlation measures the degree of relationship between two
variables.
Regression analysis is about how one variable affects another or what changes it causes to the other.
Second correlation doesn't capture causality but the degree of interrelation between the two variables.
As with Vin Diesel movies variables we're moving together but were not causing each other.
Regression is based on causality.
It shows no degree of connection but cause and effect.
Third a property of correlation is that the correlation between X and Y is the same as between y and
X..
This you can easily see from the formula which is symmetrical regressions of y on X and X on Y.
You'll different results.
Think about our example with income and education predicting income based on education makes sense.
But the opposite does not.
Finally the two methods have very different graphical representation.
Linear regression analysis is known for the best fitting line that goes through the data points and
minimizes the distance between them.
While correlation is a single point alright.
Hopefully this short video clears some doubts you had.
Stay tuned.