Let's check out the simple linear regression equation once again.
Here it is.
You have probably heard of the regression line.
Right.
When we pull up the data points on an x y plane the regression line is the best fitting line through
the data points OK.
Here's a plot with some data points.
We plot the line based on the regression equation.
The great points that are scattered are the observed values be 0.
As we said earlier is a constant and is the intercept of the regression line with the y axis.
B One is the slope of the regression line.
It shows how much Y changes for each unit change of x.
The distance between the observed values and the regression line is the estimator of the error term
Epsilon its point estimate is called residual.
Now if you draw a perpendicular from an observed point to the regression line the intercept between
that perpendicular and the regression line is a point with a y value equal to y hat.
As we said earlier given in x y.
What is the value predicted by the regression line OK our next lesson will be an example of what we
have seen so far.