It's time for an example isn't it.
What we have here is a database with S.A.T. grades and college GPA.
All right.
So we have a sample of 100 students who studied in a given college.
Their total S.A.T. scores include critical reading mathematics and writing and the GPA is the grade
point average they had at graduation.
So what would we do if we had to use our knowledge from previous sections.
The most logical thing would be to see what is the correlation between the two variables S.A.T. grades
and GPA.
The simple correlation is 0.6 for we could then further test if this correlation is significant.
By using hypothesis testing and we would confirm that the two variables are correlated then what these
tests did not give us any information about any under or over achievers.
We have no predictive ability except for seeing the two scores move in the same direction.
Well this is a problem that regression analysis is designed to address.
So let's get on to it.
You can see two scatter plots in the first one on the x axes.
We have a students essay score and on the way axes his GPA in the second one the situation is reversed
on the x axis.
We have the GPA and on the y axes the S.A.T. score we have also included the regression lines.
All right we have two regressions right.
Should we use both to make predictions.
Well this is the hardest part of regression analysis.
In this case one provides a valuable insight and the other is plain wrong and utterly receivable.
The two variables are definitely correlated.
We already tested that.
But what's the causal relationship if there is one.
Let's think about the problem you attend the S.A.T. and get a score with this score you apply to college.
The next four years you attend college and graduate receiving many grades forming your GPA.
So that's your timeline.
What does this mean.
Well the S.A.T. test is taken before you see any exams in college and have a GPA actually three to five
years before that.
Is there any logic in predicting S.A.T. scores using your college graduation GPA.
No there isn't.
This is like predicting how much you spend yesterday based on how much money you found on the street
today.
No logic whatsoever.
Therefore the second regression is meaningless.
What's the takeaway.
Whenever you find data that looks regrettable you should not dive straight into regression analysis
caution and logic should be applied beforehand.
All right.
So I am saying we should predict college GPA using S.A.T. scores but don't believe me just yet use your
logic instead ask yourself what's rationale.
Well the S.A.T. is considered one of the best estimators of intellectual capacity and capability on
average if you did well on your S.A.T. you will do well in college and at the workplace.
Almost all colleges across the USA are using the S.A.T. as a proxy for admission.
The S.A.T. stood the test of time and established itself as the leading exam for college admission.
It is safe to say our regression makes sense OK after we've cleared things up we know which of the two
graphs we should focus on.
You can see the best fitting line between the points.
Also known as the regression line our dependent variable.
Why is college GPA the independent variable x is the S.A.T. score.
A student received the equation that determines the regression line is why hat equals zero point for
8 plus 0.00 1 5 times x OK.
How can we use this equation.
Say you got 1700 on your S.A.T. you plug it in and get a GPA of 3.0 or 3.
Interpreting this result is if you attended the specific college and were admitted with an S.A.T. score
of 1700.
The model predicts you will graduate with a GPA of 3.0 3 What if you got 2000 on your S.A.T..
Your GPA would then be near 3.4 8.
You get the gist of how powerful regression analysis can be.
However there are pitfalls.
What if you've got 2400 on the S.A.T..
Predicted GPA is 4.00 8 from more than the maximum.
Here we touch upon the limitations of regression analysis as the maximum S.A.T. score we had in our
sample was 2050.
It is not correct to make predictions for data points that are outside the regress data.
A possible rationale may be people that go over 2050 on the S.A.T. went to better universities where
it is much harder to get such a high GPA.
All the data was coming from the same college.
Therefore the profile of a typical student there is very specific.
It may be an engineering college or an arts college.
These factors and many more affect the result.
So you should know your data but don't worry we will see enough examples so you will become confident
with identifying and interpreting regressions.
Keep up the good work and thanks for watching.