Hi and welcome to our second practical example let me introduce you to the topic.
You are a data analysis for Al Bundy's shoe shop.
Al Bundy is a U.S. based company established 30 years ago.
It also operates in Canada the U.K. and Germany.
The firm sells mid to high end shoes ranging from 120 to 200 dollars while the shoes are of high quality.
You have lots of inventory never sold.
The shoes collect dust on store shelves.
Inventory management is a common problem.
Many if not most shops cannot determine the right number of items they need to keep in stock.
The opposite problem arises too.
Shops don't supply an adequate amount of goods and fail to meet the demand in their market.
For instance you have surely entered a shoe shop but could not buy a specific pair of shoes because
they did not have them in stock.
In this example we will examine the opposite problem.
Having too much inventory.
This is a more significant problem for the company as it means the company has invested in producing
or purchasing the product but could not sell it.
All right.
One way to solve this problem is by using confidence intervals.
We have seen many examples.
But here's a real life one we can see a database with the sales information about Al Bundy shop for
the years from 2014 to 2016.
There's Invoice Number Date country product ID and shop which depends on the country the cell gender
indicates if the product is designed for men or women as shoes differ greatly depending on gender.
Next we have shoe size.
Apart from the US size system I have also included the European and the UK ones so it is easier for
you to understand the data.
If you are used to the other systems This file will be provided for you and you can check the shoe size
conversion table if you would like to do that.
Finally there is the unit price for that sale and the discount that applies.
Let's begin our analysis.
First we should determine if that sample or population data.
It's obviously a sample not the population of sales given we have just three years of data.
Second we want to get to know the data set better.
There are two big subgroups in our data men's shoes and women choose they are different and bundling
them when making predictions will yield deceiving results not only feet differ by gender but also there
are different shoe types and models.
Our problem is related to inventory management.
Therefore we should divide our inventory and then count the frequencies the frequencies will give us
a better idea of the data OK.
A good way to do that is to divide the data by shoe size.
I would also like to see it.
Country wise we already noted division by gender is also needed so we have three dimensions shoe size
country and gender.
A possible solution is to create two tables one for men's shoes and one for women's shoes and then proceed
normally.
That's what I will do.
Here are the two tables in the fall provided in the resources section.
You can see the formula I use to calculate the frequencies while Excel may be sloppy.
It is still powerful to use confidence intervals.
We must have normally distributed data.
While this sounds restrictive for all practical applications it isn't.
We can simply apply our good old friend the central limit theorem when we are in the presence of a sum
or average of many observations.
We can assume normality in our case we are calculating average sales for a period.
Given that Al Bundy shop has been operating for over 30 years silty applies and we can safely continue
with our inference OK.
We want to estimate the number of shoes that are likely to be sold.
A 95 percent confidence interval will give us such information.
We will take the last 12 months of sales and make a prediction.
Let's do this only for men's shoes as the main problem is identical for both genders.
Since people have different shoe sizes we will have to calculate 17 confidence intervals one for each
size.
Let's get to it.
First we need to calculate the means.
Here they are next.
We do not know the population variance in our sample comprises just 12 observations.
We have to use the t statistic.
This problem refers to the lesson on one population with population variance unknown.
We have a sample of 12 observations therefore we are looking for the t statistic for a 95 percent confidence
interval with 11 degrees of freedom.
It is two point eighteen.
Next we will compute the standard errors we will use the good old formula.
While it is unnecessary to go through this step as we have everything we need I will still show you
the margins of error as it may be interesting for some of you to examine.
Finally the confidence intervals are given by the following formula.
And this is how they look after the calculations have been carried out.
The result we obtained could be interpreted as follows In 95 percent of the cases.
The true population mean of the sales for each shoe size will fall into the respective interval as we
don't want to be low on stock.
A possible solution to the problem is to get as many pairs of shoes as the closest number to the upper
limit of the confidence interval.
In this way you will be almost certain you won't run out of stock and shoes won't be waiting forever
in your storage unit.
Therefore we should get four pairs of men's shoes size 6 3 pairs of men's shoe size 6.5 and so on.
Mostly we should prepare ourselves with size 9.5 and size 16 won't yield in any sales.
Sorry for those of you it's size 16 feet.
I know it is hard enough to find shoes.
But this company won't be selling any.
All right.
We are almost done here before you go.
I'd like to show you another application of confidence intervals.
Let's say we want to use a confidence interval to see if two shops are selling the same number of shoes.
We want to know with 95 percent confidence by how much one shop outperforms the other in terms of sales.
You can see two tables representing the sales of women's shoes in two German shops their codes are G.R.
one and two.
Once again we have data for 2016.
Now an assumption we have to make is that the same people don't buy pairs of shoes from different shops.
Logically it makes sense that in the same year the same people don't go around different shops of the
same brand to buy shoes.
Even if this happens it is an exception not the norm.
Therefore we can say that two samples are independent.
Once again we don't know the population variance but given this is the same market in the same country
we can assume it is equal.
This implies we're in the case of independent samples with population variance.
Unknown but assumed to be equal in the previous case.
We need to calculate the means and the sample variances here.
We must calculate a pooled variance which is an unbiased estimator of the population variance.
We're in the case where we have to use the statistic with 12 plus 12 minus two degrees of freedom for
a 95 percent confidence.
What we get from the table is 2.0 7.
The respective margins of error are given by the well-known formula.
Finally the 95 percent confidence intervals are determined by the means and the margins of error.
We get these 15 intervals.
Zero is a part of all of them except for the unsellable size for all confidence intervals star in the
negatives and finish in the positives.
This implies we cannot conclude one shop sells more shares than the other for any size.
What it seems like we have no great insight.
That's not entirely true.
The confidence intervals we got are not consistently for one shop having higher sales or the other.
This is evident from the fact that some are mostly negative while others are mostly positive.
That is to show that for some sizes GBR one is likely to sell more wealth for others vice versa.
However our decision was that using this methodology and level of confidence we cannot really identify
which shop is selling more.
They are identical the insight we get is these two shops are so balanced in sales they may share the
same warehouse or exchange pairs of shoes to achieve better results.
They can be bundled together for any analysis action or decision needed.
On average they will probably move together if one noticeably outperforms the other.
We may be sure something that wasn't observed before is going on as they are predicted to remain identical.
All right.
Time to wrap up this lesson in the next section.
We will examine hypothesis testing.
Thanks for watching.