So far we introduce quite a few notions about regressions.
Most statistics books start by introducing regression assumptions directly but we preferred to talk
about the intuition behind regressions first and then introduce you to regression assumptions.
Now that we have seen quite a few lessons we are ready to introduce regression assumptions here.
We divide them into five assumptions.
You should know all of them and consider them before you perform regression analysis.
We will have a separate lesson for each one.
The first one is linearity.
It is called a linear regression.
As we said earlier there are other types of regressions with more sophisticated models.
The linear regression is the simplest one and assumes linearity each independent variable is multiplied
by a coefficient and summed up to predict the value.
The second one is in Donje linearity of regressors.
Mathematically this is expressed as the covariance of the error and the axes is zero for any error or
x.
The third assumption is normality in Homosassa Adeste history of the error term.
Normality means the error term is normally distributed.
The expected value of the error is zero as we expect to have no errors on average almost good s Tisci
in plain English means constant variance.
We will discuss it thoroughly later.
The fourth assumption is no autocorrelation.
Mathematically the covariance of any two error terms is zero.
That's the assumption that would usually stop you from using a linear regression in your analysis and
the last one is no multi-collinearity multi-collinearity is observed when two or more variables have
a high correlation between each other.
OK these are the main regression assumptions.
They are crucial for regression analysis as the purpose of this section was to help you understand regressions.
You should not skip any lectures about assumptions at your workplace.
The biggest mistake you can make is to perform a regression that violates one of these assumptions.