The first assumption we will discuss is linearity as we explained earlier a linear regression is the
simplest non-trivial relationship.
It is called linear because the equation is linear.
Each independent variable is multiplied by a coefficient and summed up to predict the value of the dependent
variable.
How can you verify if the relationship between two variables is linear.
The easiest way is to choose an independent variable x one and plot it against the dependent y on a
scatterplot if the data points form a pattern that looks like a straight line then a linear regression
model is suitable.
Let's see a case where the assumption is violated after pulling another variable x 2 against Y on a
scatterplot we see there is no straight line that fits the data.
Well actually a curved line would be a very good fit using a linear regression would not be appropriate.
All clear linearity seems restrictive but there are easy fixes for it.
You can run a non linear regression or transform your relationship.
There are exponential and logarithmic transformations that can help with that.
The quadratic relationship we saw in this video could be easily transformed into a straight line with
the appropriate methods.
The takeaway is if the relationship is nonlinear you should not use the data before transforming it
appropriately.
That summarized linearity next assumption is in Dodge NHT of regressors.
What exactly does it mean.
We'll see in the next lesson.
Thanks for watching.