Okay great.
So far we've seen assumptions 1 and 2.
Here's the third one it comprises of three parts normality zero mean and homo Adeste history of the
era term.
The first one is easy.
We assumed the error term is normally distributed.
Normal Distribution is not required for creating the regression but for making inferences remember all
regression tables were full of T statistics and statistics.
Well these things work because we assume normality of the error return.
What should we do if the error term is not normally distributed.
You probably remember the theorem we studied earlier in the course right.
Yes that's right.
The central limit theorem for large samples.
The central limit theorem applies for the error terms too.
Therefore we can consider normality as a given for us.
What about a zero mean of error terms.
Well if the mean is not expected to be 0 then the line is not the best fitting one.
However having an intercept solves that problem.
So in real life it is unusual to violate this part of the Assumption and hope most cadet's Tisci.
What's that about.
It means to have equal variance.
So the error terms should have equal variance one with the other.
What if there was a pattern in the variance.
Well an example of a dataset where errors have a different variance.
Looks like this starting close to the regression line and going further away.
This would imply that for smaller values of the independence and dependent variables we would have a
better prediction than for the bigger values.
And I assure you we really don't like this uncertainty.
Let's see a real life example most examples related to income are heteros Godet stick with varying variants.
If a person is poor he or she spends a constant amount of money on food entertainment clothes etc..
The wealthier an individual is the higher the variability of his expenditure.
For example a poor person may be forced to eat eggs or potatoes everyday.
Both meals cost a similar amount of money.
A wealthy person however may go to a fancy gourmet restaurant where truffles are served with expensive
champagne one day and stay home and boil eggs the next day.
The variability of his spending habits is tremendous.
Therefore we expect heteros could TCD well then.
Is there a way to circumvent heteros get past TCD first check for omitted variable bias.
That's always an idea.
After that you can look for outliers and try to remove them.
Finally we shouldn't forget about a statistician's best friend.
The log transformation naturally log stands for a logarithm.
You can change the scale of the graph to a log scale for each observation in the dependent variable
calculate its natural log and then create a regression between the log of Y and the independent X's.
Conversely you can take the independent X that is causing you trouble and do the same let's see an example
this is a scatterplot that represents a high level of heteros get past history on the left hand side
of the chart.
The variance of the error is small while on the right it is high.
Here's the model as x increases by 1 unit y grows by B1 units.
Let's transform the x variable to a new variable called log of X and plot the data.
This is the new result.
Changing the scale of x would reduce the width of the graph.
You can see how the points came closer to each other from left to right.
The new model is called a semi log model.
What if we transform the Y scale instead in a logically to what happened previously.
We would expect the height of the graph to be reduced.
That's the result.
This looks like good linear regression material doesn't it.
The heteros Adeste history we observed earlier is almost gone.
This new model is also called a semi log model.
Its meaning is as x increases by 1 unit Y changes by B 1 percent.
This is a very common transformation.
Sometimes we want or need to change both scales to log.
The result is a log to log model.
We shrink the graph in height and end with.
This is the result the improvement is noticeable but not game changing.
However we may be sure the assumption is not violated.
The interpretation is for each percentage point change in x y changes by B1 percentage points.
If you've done economics you would recognize that such a relationship is known as plasticity.
All right we are done here.
Three assumptions down two to go.
Great work.