The penultimate assumption is the No autocorrelation assumption.
It is also known as No serial correlation.
This is my least favorite as it cannot be relaxed mathematically it looks like this.
Errors are assumed to be uncorrelated.
Where can we observe serial correlation between errors.
It is highly unlikely to find it in data taken at one moment of time known as cross-sectional data.
However it is very common in time series data.
Think about stock prices every day you have a new quote for the same stock.
These new numbers you see have the same underlying asset with them getting too much into the finance.
Ideally you want them to be random or predicted by macro factors such as GDP tax rate political events
and so on.
Unfortunately it is common in underdeveloped markets to see patterns in the stock prices.
There is a well-known phenomenon called The Day Of The Week effect.
It consists in disproportionately high returns on Fridays and low returns on Mondays.
There is no consensus of the true nature of the day of the week effect.
One possible explanation proposed by Nobel Prize winner Emerton Miller is that investors don't have
time to read all the news immediately.
So they do it over the weekend the first day to respond to the negative information is on Mondays.
Then during the week their advisors give them new positive information and they start buying on Thursdays
and Fridays.
Another famous explanation is given by the distinguished financer Kenneth French who suggested firms
delay bad news for the weekends.
So markets react on Mondays.
Whatever the reason there is a correlation of the errors when building regressions about stock prices.
The first observation the sixth the eleventh and the fifth onwards would be Monday's the fifth tenth
and so on would be Friday's errors on Mondays would be biased downwards and errors for Fridays would
be biased upwards.
The mathematics of the linear regression does not consider this.
It assumes errors should be randomly spread around the regression line.
So how does one detect autocorrelation.
A common way is to plot all the residuals on a graph and look for patterns.
If you can't find any you're safe but what's the remedy.
You may ask.
The remedy is there is no remedy.
I told you in the beginning of this lecture you cannot relax this assumption.
The only thing you can do is avoid using a linear regression in such a setting.
There are other types of regressions that deal with time series data.
It is possible to use an auto regressive model a moving average model or even an auto regressive moving
average model.
And I'm not done yet.
There is also an auto regressive integrated moving average model.
Make your choice as you will but don't use the linear regression model when error terms are auto correlated
our next lesson will be a lot more encouraging.
I promise.
See you there.