The last assumption is no multi-collinearity.
We observe multi-collinearity when two or more variables have high correlation.
Let's exemplify this point with an equation A is equal to two plus 5 times B A and B are two variables
with an exact linear combination.
A can be represented using B and B can be represented using a in a model containing A and B we would
have perfect multi-collinearity.
This imposes a big problem to our regression model as the coefficients will be wrongly estimated.
The reasoning is that if a can be represented using B there is no point using both.
We can just keep one of them all right.
Another example would be two variables C and D with a correlation of 90 percent.
If we had a regression model using C and D We would also have multi-collinearity although not perfect
here.
The assumption is still violated and poses a problem to our model.
Usually real life examples are helpful so let's provide one.
There are two bars in the neighborhood bonkers and the Shakespeare bar.
We want to predict the market share of bankers.
Most people living in the neighborhood drink only beer in the bars.
So a good approximation would be a model with three variables.
The price of half a pint of beer at bonkers the price of a pint of beer at bonkers and the price of
a pint of beer at Shakespear's.
This is logical right.
If one bar raises prices people would simply switch bars so the price in one bar is a predictor of the
market share of the other bar.
All right.
Where's the problem.
Half a pint of beer at bonkers costs around $1 and one pint costs 190 bonkers tries to gain market share
by cutting its price to 90 cents.
It cannot keep the price of one pint at 190 because people would just buy two times half a pint for
one dollar eighty cents.
Bonkers management lowers the price of the pint of beer to 1.70.
Next we run a regression based on these three variables.
The p value for the pint of beer at bonkers and half a pint at bonkers show they are insignificant.
Why the underlying logic behind ever model was so rigid.
Well no multi-collinearity is an assumption of the calculations behind the regression.
The price of half a pint and a full pint at bonkers definitely move together.
This messed up the calculations of the computer and it provided us with wrong estimates and wrong p
values.
So how do we fix it.
There are three types of fixes.
The first one is to drop one of the two variables.
The second is to transform them into one variable.
The third possibility is tricky.
If you are super confident in your skills you can keep them both while treating them with extreme caution.
The correct approach depends on the research at hand.
Multi-collinearity is a big problem but it is also the easiest to notice before creating the regression.
Find the correlation between each two pairs of the independent variables and you will know if a multi-collinearity
problem may arise.