You were probably watching this course because you want to learn the appropriate statistics to perform
different tests.
However before we can start testing we have to get acquainted with the types of variables we usually
encounter different types of variables required different types of statistical tests as such it is key
to be able to classify the data you are working with we can crucify data in two main ways based on its
type and on its measurement level.
Let's start from the types of data we can have.
There is categorical and numerical data categorical data describes categories or groups.
One example is car brands like Mercedes BMW and Audi they show different categories.
Another instance is answers to yes and no questions.
If I ask questions like Are you currently enrolled in a university or do you own a car.
Yes and no would be the two groups of answers that can be obtained.
This is categorical data.
Numerical data on the other hand as its name suggests represents numbers.
It is further divided into two subsets discrete and continuous discrete data can usually be counted
in a finite matter.
A good example would be the number of children that you would want to have.
Even if you don't know exactly how many you were absolutely sure that the value will be an integer such
as 0 1 2 or even 10.
Another instance is grades on the S.A.T. exam.
You may get 1000 1560 1570 or 2400.
What is important for a variable to be defined as discrete is that you can imagine each member of the
dataset knowing that SH scores range from 600 to 2400 and 10 points separate all possible scores that
can be obtained is key.
It's easier to understand discrete data by saying it's the opposite of continuous data continuous data
is infinite and impossible to count.
For instance your weight can take on every value in some range.
Let's dig a bit deeper into this.
You get on the scale and the screen shows 150 pounds or sixty point 0 3 8 9 kilograms.
But this is just an approximation.
If you gain zero point zero one pound the figure on the scale is unlikely to change.
Put your new weight will be one hundred fifty point zero one pounds or sixty eight point zero for three
four kilograms.
Now think about sweating every drop of sweat reduces your weight by the weight of that drop.
But a scale is unlikely to capture that change.
The process of losing and gaining weight occurs all the time.
Your exact weight is a continuous variable.
It can take on an infinite amount of values no matter how many digits there are after the dot.
To sum it up your weight can vary by incomprehensibly small amounts and is continuous while the number
of children you want to have is directly understandable and is discrete.
Alright these were the types of data in our next lesson.
We will explore the levels of measurement.