In our previous video we distinguish between categorical and numerical data.
Furthermore we saw that numerical data can be discrete and continuous.
It's time to move on to the other classification levels of measurement.
These can be split into two groups qualitative and quantitative data.
They are very intuitive.
So don't worry qualitative data can be nominal or ordinal nominal values or like the categories we talked
about just now Mercedes BMW or Audi or like the four seasons Winter spring summer and autumn they are
numbers and cannot be put in any order.
Ordinal data on the other hand consists of groups and categories but follows a strict order.
Imagine you have been asked to rate your lunch and the options are disgusting.
Unappetising neutral tasty and delicious although we have words and not numbers.
It is obvious that these preferences are ordered from negative to positive.
Thus the data is qualitative ordinal.
OK so what about quantitative variables.
Well as you may have guessed by now they are split into two groups interval and ratio intervals and
ratios are both represented by numbers but have one major difference ratios have a true zero and intervals
don't.
For example length is a ratio variable.
You all know that 0 inches or 0 feet means no length with temperature.
However we have a different story.
It is usually an interval variable.
Let me explain.
Usually it is expressed in Celsius or Fahrenheit.
They are both interval variables zero degrees Celsius or zero degrees Fahrenheit don't mean anything
as the absolute zero temperature is actually negative 273 point fifteen degrees Celsius or negative
four hundred fifty nine point sixty seven degrees Fahrenheit.
However we can easily say that 80 degrees Fahrenheit is less than 100 degrees Fahrenheit.
In the case of interval variables the difference is meaningful but the zero is not continuing this temperature
example.
There is a nother scale Kelvins.
According to it the absolute minimum temperature is zero degrees Kelvin.
Therefore if the degrees are stated in Kelvins the variable will be a ratio.
So numbers like two three ten ten point five pi etc. can be both an interval or a ratio measurement.
But you have to be careful with the context you are using them in.
All right we've quickly gone through the types of data and the measurement levels.
Stick around to see the types of graphs that are used on a daily basis when performing statistical analysis.