Now that we've seen the different types of data and levels of measurement we can have we are ready to
explore different graphs and tables which will allow us to visually represent the data we are working
with visualizing data is the most intuitive way to interpret it.
So it will be great if we learn how to do that.
As you may recall there are two types of variables categorical and numerical.
In this video we will focus on categorical variables.
The most common ways to visualize them are frequency distribution tables bar charts pie charts and Pareto
diagrams.
First let's see what a frequency distribution table looks like.
It has two columns.
The category itself and the corresponding frequency.
Imagine you own a car shop and you sell only German cars.
The table below shows the categories of cars.
Audi BMW and Mercedes and their frequency or in plain English the number of units sold by organizing
your data.
This way you can compare the different brands and see that Audi has been sold the most.
No preference is on my side.
However tables aren't much fun are they using the same table.
We can construct a bar chart.
The vertical axis shows the number of units sold while each bar represents a different category.
Indicated on the horizontal axes in this way it is much much clear that ADI is the best selling brand
OK let's represent the same data with a pie chart in order to build one.
We need to calculate the percentage of the total of each brand in statistics.
This is known as relative frequency.
Naturally all relative frequencies add up to 100 percent.
Pie charts are especially useful when we not only want to compare items among each other but also to
see their share of the total this example could be easily transformed into a business example of market
share.
Market share is so predominantly represented by pie charts that if you search for market share in google
images you would get only pie charts.
Imagine that the data in our table is representing the sales of Audi BMW and Mercedes in a single German
city St. bàn.
The chart will show us the market share that each of these brands has Leslie.
We have the Pareto diagram.
In fact a Pareto diagram is nothing more than a special type of bar chart where categories are shown
in descending orders of frequency by frequency.
Statisticians mean the number of occurrences of each item.
As we said earlier in our example that's exactly the number of units sold.
Let's go back to our frequency distribution table and ordered the brands by frequency.
Now we can create the bar chart based on our reorder table and voila we almost have a Pareto diagram.
There is one last touch to make it one a curve on the same graph showing the cumulative frequency cumulative
frequency is the sum of the relative frequencies.
It starts at the frequency of the first brand.
Then we add the second the third and so on until it finishes at 100 percent.
This polygon a line is measured by a different vertical axes on the right of the graph.
At the end of its vertices it shows the sum total of the categories to its left see how the Pareto diagrams
combines the strong sides of the bar and the pie chart.
It is easy to compare the data both between categories and as a part of the total.
Furthermore if this was a market share graph you could easily see the market share of the top two or
top five companies.
These are the main ways in which we visually represent categorical data.
In our next lecture we will get acquainted with the most useful graphs and tables for numerical data.
Thanks for watching.