OK.
Excellent.
We already know how to create graphs and tables for categorical variables in this lesson.
We're going to do the same for numerical variables and given that numerical data is the main focus of
this course.
We will spend a couple of lessons on this topic.
Now whenever we want to plot data it is best to first order it in a table.
So as we did with categorical variables Let's start by creating a frequency distribution table.
Here's a list of 20 different numbers.
If we arrange them in a frequency table like the one we use for categorical variables we would obtain
a table with 20 rows each of them representing one number of a corresponding frequency of one as each
number occurs exactly one time this table would be impractical for any analysis right.
Well when we deal with numerical variables it makes much more sense to group the data into intervals
and then find the corresponding frequencies.
In this way we make a summary of our data that allows for a meaningful visual representation.
How do we choose these intervals.
Generally statisticians prefer working with the groups of data that contain 5 to 20 intervals.
This way the summary can be useful.
However this varies from case to case and the correct choice of intervals largely depends on the amount
of data we are working with in our example.
We will divide the data into five intervals of equal length.
The simple formula that we use is as follows.
The interval with is equal to the largest number minus the smallest number divided by the number of
desired intervals.
In our case the length of the interval should be 100 minus 1 divided by 5.
The result is nineteen point eight.
Now we want to round this number up in order to reach a neater representation.
Therefore our intervals will be as follows 1 to 21 21 to 41 41 to 61 61 to 81 an 81 to 101.
Each interval has a with of 20 OK.
Let's try to construct the frequency distribution table will have to work with two components intervals
and frequency as we can see from the table.
There are 2 numbers in the first interval.
For in the second three and the third six in the fourth and five in the fifth interval.
For many analysis it is useful to calculate the relative frequency of the data points.
As we said in a previous video the relative frequency is the frequency of a given interval as a part
of the total.
Let's add another column to our table and name it relative frequency.
So the interval from 1 to 20 has an absolute frequency of 2 but a relative frequency of two divided
by the total of 20 numbers which gives us 10 percent and so on as we fill the table.
All right this is how we calculate relative frequencies.
Now that we have summarized the raw data we can start plotting it.