The most common graph used to represent numerical data is the histogram first we'll learn how to create
it and then we'll provide a description of the way the data is represented.
We are going to use the frequency distribution table from our previous example to help us.
Here it is as you can see it looks like a bar chart but actually conveys very different information
as in the bar chart.
The vertical axis is the numerical type and shows the absolute frequency.
This time though the horizontal axes is numerical 2.
To use the other classification we already know it is quantitative data of the interval type.
All right so each bar has with equal to the interval and height equal to the frequency.
Notice how the different bars are touching.
This is to show that there is continuation between the intervals each interval ends where the next one
starts in the bar chart.
However different bars represented different categories.
So the bars were completely separate ok.
Sometimes it is useful to plot the intervals against the relative rather than the absolute frequency
as you can see the histogram looks the same visually but gives different information to the audience
remember relative frequency is made up of percentages.
There is one last thing to note here.
We may create a histogram with an equal intervals.
An example is designing age groups.
You've likely completed some survey where you were asked about your age and the possible answers were
18 to 25 then 25 to 30 30 to 35 and so on until 60 plus clearly the interval widths vary and reflect
different focus groups for the experiment at hand.
An explanation for this choice may be young adults under-25 cannot afford the product while adults over
60 have no interest in the product.
In any case you should be quite experienced to accurately design and interpret such groups.
It is highly recommended that you stick with the equal with intervals until you gain enough experience.
OK great this is how we can build a histogram in order to represent numerical data.
Stay tuned for our next lesson where we will see graphs that allow us to observe the relationship between
variables.