So far we covered graphs that represent only one variable but how do we represent relationships between
two variables.
In this video we'll explore across tables and scatter plots.
Once again we have a division between categorical and numerical variables.
Let's start with categorical variables.
The most common way to represent them is using cross tables or as some statisticians call them contingency
tables.
Imagine you are an investment manager and you manage stocks bonds and real estate investments for three
different investors.
Each of them has a different idea of risk and hence their money is allocated in a different way.
Among the three asset classes across table representing all the data looks in the following way you
can clearly see the rows showing the different type of investment that's been made and the columns with
each investor's allocation.
It is good practice to calculate the totals of each row and column as it is often useful in further
analysis.
Notice that the subtotals of the rows give us total investment in stocks bonds and real estate.
On the other hand the subtotals of the columns gives us the holdings of each investor once we have created
a cross table we can proceed to visualizing the data onto a plane a very useful chart.
In such cases is a variation of the bar chart called the side by side bar chart.
It represents the holdings of each investor in the different types of assets.
Stocks are in green.
Bonds are in red.
And real estate is in blue.
The name of this type of chart comes from the fact that for each investor the categories of assets are
represented side by side.
In this way we can easily compare asset holdings for a specific investor or among investors.
Easy right.
All graphs are very easy to create and read once you have identified the type of data you're dealing
with and decided on the best way to visualize it.
Finally we would like to conclude with a very important graph.
The scatterplot this is used when representing two numerical sets of data for this example we have gathered
the reading and writing S.A.T. scores of 100 individuals.
Let me first show you the graph before analyzing it.
All right.
First they say scores are or component range from 200 to 800 points.
That is why our data is bounded within the range of 200 to 800 circuit.
Our vertical axes shows the writing scores while the horizontal axes contains the reading scores.
Third there are 100 students and their results correspond to a specific point on the graph.
Each point gives us information about a particular student's performance.
For example this is Jane she scored 300 on writing but 550 on the reading part scatter plots usually
represent lots and lots of observations when interpreting a scatterplot a statistician is not expected
to look into single data points.
He would be much more interested in getting the main idea of how the data is distributed OK.
The first thing we see is that there is an obvious up trend.
This is because lower writing scores are usually obtained by students with lower reading scores and
higher writing scores have been achieved by students with higher reading scores.
This is logical right.
Students are more likely to do well on both because the two tests are closely related.
Second we notice a concentration of students in the middle of the graph with scores in the region of
450 to 550 on both reading and writing.
Remember that we said that scores could be anywhere between 200 and 800.
Well 500 is the average score one can get.
So it makes sense that a lot of people fall into that area.
Third there is a group of people with both very high writing and reading scores.
The exceptional students tend to be excellent at both components.
This is less true for bad students as their performance tends to deviate when performing different tasks.
Finally we have Jane from a minute ago.
She is far away from every observation as she scored above average on reading but poorly on writing.
This observation is called an outlier as it goes against the logic of the whole dataset.
We will learn more about outliers and how to treat them in our analysis later on in this course.
So we have gone through the basics.
We have covered populations sample's types of variables graphs and tables.
It is time for us to dive into the heart of descriptive statistics measurements of central tendency
and variability.
Thanks for watching.