Hi and welcome back.
This is the main section of this course.
It is based on the knowledge that you acquired previously.
So if you haven't been through it you may have a hard time keeping up.
Make sure you have seen all the videos about confidence intervals distribution's the tables and tea
tables and have done all the exercises.
If you've completed them already you are good to go.
Confidence Intervals provide us with an estimation of where the parameters are located.
However when you are making a decision you need a yes or no answer.
The correct approach in this case is to use a test.
In this section we will learn how to perform one of the fundamental tasks in statistics.
Hypothesis Testing.
OK there are four steps in data driven decision making.
First you must formulate a hypothesis second.
Once you have formulated a hypothesis you will have to find the right test for your hypothesis.
Third you execute the test.
And fourth you make a decision based on the result.
Let's start from the beginning what is a hypothesis.
Though there are many ways to define it.
The most intuitive I've seen is a hypothesis is an idea that can be tested.
This is not the formal definition but it explains the point very well.
So if I tell you that apples in New York are expensive.
This is an idea or a statement but is not testable until I have something to compare it with.
For instance if I define expensive as any price higher than one dollar and seventy five cents per pound
then it immediately becomes a hypothesis.
All right what.
Something that cannot be tested with a hypothesis.
An example may be.
Would the USA do better or worse under a Clinton administration compared to a Trump administration.
Statistically speaking this is an idea but there is no data to test it therefore it cannot be a hypothesis
of a statistical test.
Actually it is more likely to be a topic of another discipline.
Conversely in statistics we may compare different U.S. presidencies that have already been completed
such as the Obama administration and the Bush administration.
As we have data on both.
All right let's get out of politics and get into hypotheses.
Here's a simple topic that can be tested according to Glassdoor the popular selling information Web
site the mean data scientists cellaring the US is one hundred thirteen thousand dollars so we wanted
to test if their estimate is correct.
There are two hypotheses that are made the null hypothesis denoted h zero and the Alternative Hypothesis
denoted h 1 or H.
The null hypothesis is the one to be tested and the alternative is everything else in our example.
The null hypothesis would be the mean data scientists salary is one hundred thirteen thousand dollars
while the alternative the mean data scientists salary is not one hundred thirteen thousand dollars.
Now you would want to check if one hundred thirteen thousand is close enough to the true mean predicted
by our sample in case it is you would accept the null hypothesis.
Otherwise you would reject the null hypothesis.
The concept of the null hypothesis is similar to innocent until proven guilty.
We assume that the mean salary is one hundred thirteen thousand dollars and we try to prove otherwise.
All right this was an example of a two sided or a two tailed test.
You can also form one sided or OneTel tests say your friend Paul told you that he thinks data scientists
are more than one hundred twenty five thousand dollars per year.
You don't him so you design a test to see who is right.
The null hypothesis of this test would be the mean data scientists salary is more than one hundred twenty
five thousand dollars.
The alternative will cover everything else.
Thus the mean data scientists salary is less than or equal to one hundred twenty five thousand dollars.
It is important to note that outcomes of tests refer to the population parameter rather than the sample
statistic as such.
The result that we get is for the population another crucial consideration is that generally the researcher
is trying to reject the null hypothesis.
Think about the null hypothesis as the status quo and the alternative as the change or innovation that
challenges that status quo.
In our example Paul was representing the status quo which we were challenging.
All right.
That's all for now in the next lectures.
We'll see some examples and learn how to make data driven decisions.