High again.
So you know what a hypothesis is and you have an idea of how to form the know and alternative hypotheses
in this lesson we all understand the reason why hypothesis testing works.
Imagine that the actual average grade of all students in a UK university is 55 percent.
The University Dean however believes that on average students obtain 70 percent.
Of course you can't just agree with his opinion.
So you start testing the hypothesis is the population mean grade is 70 percent.
The alternative hypothesis is the population mean grade is different than 70 percent.
So why does hypothesis testing work.
We assume that the population of grades is normally distributed.
The true population mean is fifty five percent.
The idea is to test if 70 percent is the true mean.
Or in our example if 70 percent is close enough to 55 percent this part is called the rejection region.
If the no hypothesis value is inside the rejection region you reject the null hypothesis.
Now imagine that the old Dean who got fired recently told you that the mean grade is 56 percent.
In that case if you want to test his opinion the null hypothesis would be the population mean is equal
to 56 percent.
This value is much closer to 55 percent and far away from the rejection region.
You will most likely accept the no hypothesis in statistical jargon.
You cannot say that 56 percent is not the population mean this will all become clear soon enough.
There is one more important part of testing the significance level the significance level is denoted
by Alpha.
It is the probability of rejecting the null hypothesis if it is true.
The rejection region depends on the Alpha as pointed in the graph.
Typical values for Alpha are zero point zero or 1 0.05 and zero point one.
It is a value that you select based on the certainty you need.
In most cases the choice of Alpha is determined by the context you are operating in.
For example if you need to test if a machine is working properly you would expect it to make little
or no mistakes as you want to be very precise.
You should pick a low significance level such as 0.01 the famous Coca-Cola glass bottle is 12 ounces.
If the machine pours twelve point one ounces some of the liquid will be spilled and the label will be
damaged as well.
So in certain situations we need to be as accurate as possible.
However if we were analyzing human or company behavior we would expect a more random behavior and hence
a higher degree of error.
For example if we want to predict how much Coca-Cola consumers drink on average the difference between
12 ounces and twelve point one ounces will not be that crucial.
So we can choose a higher significance level alright.
Our graph so far we're showing rejection reagents for two sided tests such as the one where we tested
whether our population mean is equal to 70 percent in these cases.
The significance level Alpha is divided between the two sides of the normal distribution on the left.
We have a significance of Alpha divided by two.
And on the right we have another alpha divided by two.
This is due to the fact that the true mean could be either 55 percent or 85 percent in both cases.
We are equally likely to reject the null hypothesis but on a different side of the distribution What
about one tailed tests which look in the following way.
Is the mean lower than 70 percent.
And in each one is the mean higher or equal to 70 percent.
In this case the rejection region will only be on the right side with a significant level of alpha and
to complete the picture.
Here's a plot of the third case defined by an age zero of the mean higher than 70 percent.
All right.
In a lesson or two we'll get to real life examples.
We are almost there.
Just hold on a bit.