This lesson we'll introduce you to the three measures of central tendency.
Don't be scared by the terminology we are talking about mean median and mode even if you are familiar
with these terms.
Please stick around as we will explore their upsides and shortfalls.
Ready let's go.
The first measure we will study is the mean.
Also known as the simple average it is denoted by the Greek letter mue for a population an X bar for
a sample.
These notions will come in handy in the next section we can find the mean of a dataset by adding up
all of its components and then dividing them by the number of components contained in the data set.
The mean is the most common measure of central tendency but it has a huge downside.
It is easily affected by outliers.
Let's compare these two data sets.
These are the prices of pizza at 11 different locations in New York City and 10 different locations
in L.A..
Let's calculate the means of the two data sets using the formula for the mean in NYC.
We get $11 whereas for L.A. just 5.5 on average pizza.
New York can't be twice as expensive as in L.A. right.
Correct.
The problem is that in our sample we have included one posh place in New York where they charge $66
for a pizza.
And this doubled to mean what we should take away from this example is that the mean is not enough to
make definite conclusions.
So how can we protect ourselves from this issue.
You guessed it we can calculate the second measure the median the median is basically the middle number
in an ordered dataset.
Let's see how it works for our example.
In order to calculate the median we have to order our dataset in ascending order the median of the dataset
is the number at position end plus 1 divided by two in the ordered list where n is the number of observations
therefore the median for NYC is at the 6 position or six dollars much closer to the observed prices
than the mean of dollars right.
What about L.A..
We have just 10 observations in L.A. According to our formula the median is at position 5.5.
In cases like this the median is the simple average of the numbers.
Positions 5 and 6.
Therefore the median of L.A. prices is five point five dollars.
OK.
We have seen that the median is not affected by extreme prices which is good when we have posh New York
restaurants in a street pizza sample but we still don't get the full picture or the majority of restaurants
low cost or average.
We must introduce another measure the mode.
The mode is the value that occurs most often.
It can be used for numerical and categorical data but we will stick to our numerical example.
After counting the frequencies of each value we find that the mode of New York pizza prices is $3.
Now that's interesting.
The most common price of pizza in NYC is just $3 but the mean and median led us to believe it was much
more expensive OK let's do the same and find the mode of L.A. pizza prices from each price appears only
once.
How do we find the mode then.
Well we say that there is no mode but can I say that there are 10 modes you may ask.
Sure you can but it will be meaningless with 10 observations and an experienced statistician would never
do that.
In general you often have multiple modes usually two or three modes are tolerable.
But more than that would defeat the purpose of finding a mode.
There is one less question that we haven't answered which measure is best the NYC and L.A. example shows
us that measures of central tendency should be used together rather than independently.
Therefore there is no best.
But using only one is definitely the worst.
All right.
Now you know about the mean median and mode.
In our next video we will use that knowledge to talk about skewness.
Stay tuned and thanks for watching.