Next on our to do list are the measures of variability.
There are many ways to quantify variability.
However we will focus on the most common ones variance standard deviation and coefficient of variation
in the field of statistics we will typically use different formulas when working out the population
data and sample data.
Let's think about this for a bit.
When you have the whole population each data point is known.
So you are 100 percent sure of the measures you are calculating when you take a sample of this population
and you compute a sample statistic.
It is interpreted as an approximation of the population parameter.
Moreover if you extract 10 different samples from the same population you will get 10 different measures.
Statisticians have solved the problem by adjusting the algebraic formulas for many statistics to reflect
the issue.
Therefore we will explore both population and sample formulas as they are both used.
You must be asking yourself why there are unique formulas for the mean median and mode.
Well actually the sample mean is the average of the sample data points.
While the population mean is the average of the population data points Technically there are two different
formulas but they are computed in the same way.
OK now after this short clarification it's time to get on a variance variance measures the dispersion
of a set of data points around their mean value population variance denoted by Sigma squared is equal
to the sum of square differences between the observed values and the population mean divided by the
total number of observations.
Several variants on the other hand is denoted by s squared and is equal to the sum of squared differences
between observed sample values and the sample mean divided by the number of sample observations minus
one all right when you are getting acquainted with statistics it is hard to grasp everything right away.
Therefore let's stop for a second to examine the formula for the population and try to clarify its meaning.
The main part of the formula is its numerator.
So that's what we want to comprehend.
The sum of the differences between the observations and the mean squared.
Hmm.
So the closer the number to the mean the lower the result we will obtain.
Right.
And the further away from the mean it lies the larger the difference.
Easy but why do we elevate to the second degree.
Squaring the differences has two main purposes.
First by squaring the numbers we always get non-negative computations.
Without going too deep into the mathematics of it it is intuitive that dispersion cannot be negative
dispersion is about distance and distance cannot be negative.
If on the other hand we calculate the difference and do not elevate to the second degree we would obtain
both positive and negative values.
That when summed would cancel out leaving us with no information about the dispersion.
Second squaring amplifies the effect of large differences.
For example if the mean is 0 and you have an observation of 100 the squared spread is 10000 Alright
enough dry theory.
It's time for a practical example.
We have a population of 5 observations.
One two three four and five.
Let's find its variants.
We start by calculating the mean one plus two plus three plus four plus five divided by five equals
three.
Then we apply the formula.
We just saw one minus three squared plus two minus three squared plus three minus three squared plus
four minus three squared plus five minus three squared.
All of these components have to be divided by five.
When we do the math we get two.
So the population variance of the data set is to but what about sample variance.
This would only be suitable if we were told that these five observations were a sample drawn from a
population.
So let's imagine that's the case the sample mean is once again three the numerator is the same but the
denominator is going to be 4 instead of 5 giving us a sample variance of 2.5 to conclude the variance
topic we should interpret the result.
Why is the simple variance bigger than the population variance in the first case.
We knew the population that is we had all the data and we calculated the variance in the second case.
We were told that 1 2 3 4 and 5 was a simple drawn from a bigger population.
Now imagine the population of this sample were 1 1 1 2 3 4 5 5 and 5.
Clearly the numbers are the same but there is a concentration about the two extremes of the data set
1 and 5.
The variance of this population is two point ninety six.
So our sample variance has rightfully corrected upwards.
In order to reflect a higher potential variability This is the reason why there are different formulas
for simple and population data.
This was a very important lesson.
So please make sure you have understood it well.
You can reinforce what you have learned here by doing the exercise available in the course resources
section.
Remember the subject of statistics is only understood when practiced.