Wild variance is a common measure of data dispersion.
In most cases the figure you will obtain is pretty large and hard to compare as the unit of measurement
is squared.
The easy fix is to calculate it square root and obtain a statistic known as standard deviation in most
analysis you perform standard deviation will be much more meaningful than variance as we saw in the
previous lecture.
There are different measures for the population and sample variance.
Consequently there is also population and sample standard deviation.
The formulas are the square root of the population variance and the square root of the sample variance
respectively.
I believe there is no need for an example of the calculation right.
If you have a calculator in your hands you'll be able to do the job.
All right.
The other measure we still have to introduce is the coefficient of variation.
It is equal to the standard deviation divided by the mean.
Another name for the term is relative standard deviation.
This is an easy way to remember its formula.
It is simply the standard deviation relative to the mean as you probably guessed there is a population
and simple formula.
Once again so standard deviation is the most common measure of variability for a single dataset.
But why do we need yet another measure such as the coefficient of variation.
Well comparing the standard deviations of two different data sets is meaningless but comparing coefficients
of variation is not Aristotle once said.
Tell me I'll forget.
Show me I remember.
Involve me all understand.
To make sure you remember here's an example of a comparison between standard deviations.
Let's take the prices of pizza at 10 different places in New York.
They range from 1 to $11.
Now imagine that you only have Mexican pesos and to you the prices look more like eighteen point eight
one pesos to two hundred six point ninety one pesos.
Given the exchange rate of eighteen point eight one pesos for one dollar let's combine our knowledge
so far and find the standard deviations and coefficients of variation of these two data sets.
First we have to see if this is a sample or a population.
Are there only 11 restaurants in New York.
Of course not.
This is obviously a sample drawn from all the restaurants in the city.
Then we have to use the formulas for sample measures of variability.
Second we have to find the mean the mean in dollars is equal to 5.5 and the meat in pesos is one hundred
three point forty six.
The third step of the process is finding the sample variance.
Following the formula that we showed earlier we can obtain ten point seventy two dollars squared and
three thousand seven hundred ninety three point sixty nine peso squared the respective sample standard
deviations are three point seven dollars and sixty one point five nine pesos.
Let's make a couple of observations.
First variance gives results in squared units while standard deviation in original units.
This is the main reasons why professionals prefer to use standard deviation as the main measure of variability.
It is directly interpretable squared dollars means nothing even in the field of statistics.
Second we got standard deviations of 3.2 seven and sixty one point five nine for the same pizza at the
same eleven restaurants in New York City.
Seems wrong.
Right.
Don't worry.
It is time to use our last tool.
The coefficient of variation dividing the standard deviations by the respective means we get the two
coefficients of variation.
The result is the same 0.60.
Notice that it is not dollars.
Pesos dollars squared or pesos squared.
It is just 0.60.
This shows us the great advantage that the coefficient of variation gives us.
Now we can confidently say that the two data sets have the same variability.
Which is what we expected beforehand.
Let's recap what we have learned so far.
There are three main measures of variability variance standard deviation and coefficient of variation.
You should feel confident using all of them as we're getting closer to more complex statistical topics.
And remember Aristotle's advice involve me I'll understand.
So please don't forget to get involved with the exercises.