All right.
Excellent.
We've covered all Yuni variant measures.
Now it is time to see measures that are used when we work with more than one variable in the next two
lessons.
We'll explore measures that can help us explore the relationship between variables.
Our focus will be on covariance and the linear correlation coefficient.
Let's zoom out a bit and think of an example that is very easy to understand and will help us grasp
the nature of the relationship between two variables a bit better.
Think about real estate which is one of the main factors that determined house prices.
Their size right.
Typically larger houses are more expensive as people like having extra space.
The table that you can see here shows this data about several houses on the left side.
We can see the size of each house and on the right we have the price at which it's been listed in a
local newspaper.
We can present these data points in a scatterplot the x axes will show House's size and the y axis will
provide information about its price.
We can certainly notice a pattern.
There is a clear relationship between these variables.
We say that two variables are correlated and the main statistic to measure this correlation is called
covariance unlike variance covariance may be positive equal to zero or negative.
To understand the concept better I would like to show you the formulas that allows us to calculate the
covariance between two variables.
It is formulas with an S because once again there is a sample and population formula.
Here they are.
Since this is obviously sample data we should use the simple covariance formula.
Let's apply it in practice for the example that we saw earlier x will be the house size and y stands
for house prices.
First we need to calculate the mean size and the mean price.
Ok done.
Now let's calculate the nominator of the covariance function starting with the first house.
I'll multiply the difference between its size and the average house size by the difference between the
price of the same house and the average house price once we're ready.
We have to perform this calculation for all the houses that we have in the table and then some the numbers
we've obtained see great our sample size is five.
Now we have to divide the sum above by the sample size minus one.
The result is the covariance.
It gives us a sense of direction in which the two variables are moving.
If they go in the same direction the covariance will have a positive sign.
While if they move in the opposite directions the covariance will have a negative sign.
Finally if their movements are independent the covariance between the house size and its price will
be equal to zero.
There is just one tiny problem with covariance though it could be a number like 5 or 50 but it can also
be something like 0.00 2 3 4 5 6 or even over 30 million.
As in our example.
Totally different values.
How could one interpret such numbers proceed to the next lecture to find out how the correlation coefficient
can help us with this issue.
Thanks for watching.