Correlation adjust covariance so that the relationship between the two variables becomes easy and intuitive
to interpret the formulas for the correlation coefficient or the covariance divided by the product of
the standard deviations of the two variables.
This is either sample or population depending on the data you are working with.
We already have the standard deviations of the two data sets.
Now we'll use the formula in order to find the simple correlation coefficient.
Mathematically there is no way to obtain a correlation value greater than 1 or less than negative 1.
Remember the coefficient of variation we talked about a couple of lessons ago.
Well this concept is similar.
We've been related the strange covariance value in order to get something intuitive.
Let's examine it for a bit.
We got a simple correlation coefficient of zero point seven.
So for each foot increase in size of a house its price rises by $870.
OK what about the general case a correlation of one also known as perfect positive correlation means
that the entire variability of one variable is explained by the other variable.
In our case this means that for every additional square foot of size we would expect an increase of
let's say $1000 in the house price.
For instance five additional square feet will lead to a price increase of $5000 10 additional square
feet would lead to a price increase of $10000 and so on.
In that case the observations in our plot will form a straight line as the correlation between size
and price has to be perfect.
It would mean that the size is the only variable that determines our houses price and that we can easily
calculate a house price if we know its size.
Before we continue we must note that the correlation between two variables x and y is the same as the
correlation between y and x.
The formula is completely symmetrical with respect to both variables.
Therefore we must expect that an increase in price of $1000 will also mean that the size must be one
square foot.
Larger However logically we know that size determines price on average the bigger house you build the
more expensive it will be.
This relationship only goes this way once a house is built.
If for some reason it becomes more expensive its size doesn't increase although there is a positive
correlation.
This leads us to causality.
It is very important for any analyst or researcher to understand the direction of causal relationships
in the house business size causes the price and not vice versa.
We will explore this topic in much more detail in the regression analysis section later on.
For now it is only needed that you realize that correlation does not imply causation OK a correlation
of zero between two variables means that they are absolutely independent from each other.
We would expect a correlation of zero between the price of coffee in Brazil and the price of houses
in London right.
The two variables don't have anything in common.
Finally we can have negative correlation coefficient.
It can be perfect negative correlation of negative one or much more likely an imperfect negative correlation
of a value between negative 1 and 0.
Think of the following businesses a company producing ice cream and a company selling umbrellas.
Ice cream tends to be sold a lot more when the weather is very good and people buy umbrellas when it's
rainy.
Obviously there is a negative correlation between the two and hence when one of the companies makes
more money the other won't.
OK very good with this example.
We conclude the section on descriptive statistics in the next lesson you will see a real life database
example that applies all the knowledge you acquired in this section.
You definitely don't want to miss it.