We already saw the regression equation and an example of a regression model in this lesson we will explore
the determinants of a good regression.
This video is based on the Andover framework.
You may have heard before there are three terms we must define the sum of square totals the sum of squares
regression and the sum of squares error.
The sum of squares total denoted as s t is the square differences between the observed dependent variable
and its mean.
You can think of this as the dispersion of the observed variables around the mean.
Much like the variance we saw in descriptive statistics.
It is a measure of the total variability of the dataset.
The second term is the sum of squares regression or SSR.
It is the sum of differences between the predicted value and the mean of the dependent variable.
Think of it as a measure that describes how well your line fits the data.
If this value of SSR is equal to the sum of squares total It means your regression model captures all
observed variability and is perfect.
The last term is the sum of squares error or SS each.
As we said in one of the previous videos the error is the difference between the observed value and
the predicted value.
We usually want to minimize the error.
The smaller the error the better the estimation power of the regression.
So what is the connection among these three mathematically.
S s t is equal to ss r plus ss e.
The rationale is the following.
The total variability of the data set is equal to the variability explained by the regression line plus
the unexplained variability known as error.
Given a constant total variability.
A lower error will cause a better regression.
Conversely a higher error will cause a less powerful regression.
Makes sense right.
All right.
Based on this knowledge in our next lesson we will learn how to compare different regression models.
Thanks for watching.