High again so far we decompose the total variability of the observed data into explained and unexplained.
We've also noted the smaller the regression error the better the regression.
But this is statistics.
So there must be at least one widely used measure that describes how powerful a regression is.
Right.
Well fortunately or unfortunately depending on your attitude there is.
Let me introduce you to the R-squared the R-Squared is an intuitive and practical tool when in the right
hands it is equal to SS are divided by ss t as you should recall.
Ss r is the variability explained by the regression while S S T is the total variability of the dataset.
So what does it mean.
It's a relative measure that takes values ranging from 0 to 1 an R squared of zero means a regression
line explains none of the variability of the data and R-squared of one would mean your model explains
the entire variability of the data.
Unfortunately regression is explaining the entire variability are rare.
What you will usually observe is values ranging from 0.2 to 0.9 the immediate question.
Any student is compelled to ask is what is a good R-squared.
When do I know for sure my regression is good enough.
I regret to inform you there is no definite answer to that in the field of physics and chemistry.
Scientists are usually looking for regressions with R squared between 0.7 and 0.9.
However in social sciences such as economics finance and psychology an R-squared of 0.2 or 20 percent
of the variability explained by the model could be fantastic.
It depends on the complexity of the topic and how many variables are believed to be in play.
Think about income once more.
It may depend on your household income including your parents and spouse your education years of experience.
Country you are living in languages you speak and this may still account for less than 50 percent of
the variability of income.
Your salary is a very complex issue but you probably know that.
Let's check an example we saw before S.A.T. score and call his GPA.
We said that the S.A.T. score is one of the better determinants of intellectual capacity and capability.
The truth is that our regression had an R-squared of zero point for 0 6 or in other words as SAT scores
explained 41 percent of the variability of the college grades for our sample.
An R-squared of 41 percent is neither good nor bad but since it is far away from 90 percent we may conclude
we are missing some important information other determinants must be considered variables such as gender
income and marital status could help us understand the full picture a little better.
OK should we move on.
Wait what did I say in this section.
Don't jump into regressing.
Critical thinking is crucial before agreeing that a factor is significant.
You should try to understand why.
So let's quickly justify that claim first.
Women are more likely to outperform men in high school but then in higher education more men enter academia.
There are many biases in place here without telling you if female or male candidates are better.
Scientific research shows that a gender gap exists in education.
Gender is an important input for any regression on the topic.
The second factor we pointed out is income.
If your household income is low you are more likely to get a part time job thus you'll have less time
for studying and probably get lower grades.
If you've ever been to college you will surely remember a friend who underperformed because of this
reason.
Third if you get married and have a child you'll definitely have a lower attendance.
Contrary to what most students think when in college attendance is a significant factor for your GPA.
You may think your time is better spent when skipping a lecture but your GPA begs to differ.
All right after these clarifications let's find the bottom line.
The R squared measures the goodness of fit of your model the more factors you include in your regression
the higher the R-squared.
So should we include gender and income in our regression.
If this is in line with our research and their inclusion results in a better model we should do that.
However we'll talk about regressions with more variables later in the course.
In this lesson we built a solid understanding of how our squared functions.
Excellent.
Next we will learn how to find a regressions regression line.