OK.
Excellent so far we learned about the simple linear regression we predicted the dependent variable y
with a single regressors x.
It is time to level up.
Now we said that in real life a person's income does not depend solely on education but also their experience
the time they have spent with their current employer and so on.
House prices do not depend on solely their size but also on location and year of construction.
College GPA cannot be predicted solely by a student's S.A.T. score but also by their high school GPA
income gender and so on.
If we want to make good models we need multi-variate regressions multi-variate regressions address the
higher complexity of problems the more variables you have the more factors you are considering in a
model.
In the real world things depend on two three or even 10 or 20 factors.
All right so this is the population multivariate regression model.
It is similar to a simple regression.
The main difference is there are a bunch of independent variables not just one what we are interested
in is the multivariate regression equation.
We want to plug in numbers and predict outcomes right.
Once again why had is the inferred value and 0 is the int..
The independent variables range from x 1 to x K be 1 to be k.
Are there corresponding coefficients.
The last thing to say about multivariate regressions is that it's not about the best fitting line anymore.
Actually it stops being two dimensional and when we have over three dimensions there is no visual way
to represent the data.
So if it is not about the line what is it about.
It's a bell.
The best fitting model as we saw from the OS.
What we really want is the least sum of squared errors.
All right so how do we decrease the models error well by increasing the explanatory power of the model.
Ss e n ss are communicating vessels.
Remember each time we lower one.
The other goes higher with each additional variable.
We increase the explanatory power by zero or more than zero.
We cannot lower it more variables usually equal a better fitting model.
In the next lesson we will see how to determine the optimal number of variables to use.
Thanks for watching.