Remember when we talked about R-squared and I told you it was a very widely used measure of explanatory
power.
Well that was almost true.
We'll have to refine this measure its new version will be called the adjusted R-squared.
A statistician would always look at it when performing regression analysis.
So what does it adjust for.
Let's consider two statements we saw in the previous lessons one the R-squared measures how much of
the total variability is explained by our model and to multivariate regressions are always better than
univariate as with each additional variable you add the explanatory power may only increase or stay
the same well be adjusted r squared considers exactly that.
It measures how much of the total variability is explained by our model.
Considering the number of variables the adjusted r squared is always smaller than the R squared as it
penalizes excessive use of variables.
Think about our S.A.T. scores example.
It had an R squared of 0.4 06 and an adjusted R-squared of 0.3 9:9.
Now let's add another variable called random 1 to 3.
I've generated a variable that assigns one two or three randomly to each student.
We are 100 percent sure this variable cannot predict college GPA.
So this is our new model college GPA is equal to be zero plus be 1 times S.A.T. score plus B two times
the random variable.
Let's check out the newly created regression tables.
We can see the new R-Squared is 0.4 0 7.
So it seems we have increased the explanatory power of the model but then our enthusiasm is dampened
by the adjusted R-squared of 0.3 9 3.
We were penalized for adding an additional variable that had no strong explanatory power.
We have added information but have lost value.
The point is you should cherry pick your data to exclude useless information.
However one would assume that regression analysis is smarter than that right.
Adding an impractical variable should be pointed out by the model Well that's true.
Look at the coefficients table we have determined a coefficient for the random 1 to 3 variable but its
p value is 0.6 7:7.
Remember the null hypothesis of the test Beta 2 equals zero.
We cannot reject the no hypothesis at the 68 significance level.
This is an incredibly high p value.
Let me remind you that for a call efficient to be statistically significant We want a p value of less
than 0.05.
Our conclusion is that the variable random one to three not only worsens the explanatory power of the
model reflected by a lower adjusted r squared but is also insignificant.
Therefore it should be dropped altogether.
Dropping useless variables is important.
You can see the original model change from Y had equal zero point to for 7 plus zero point zero zero
two times x 1.0 point 0 1 2 times x 2 2 y had equal zero point 4 8 0 3 plus 0.00 1 5 times x 1.
The choice of the third variable drastically affected our other predictors.
Whenever you have one variable ruining the model you should not use this model altogether because the
bias of this variable is reflected into the coefficients of the other variables.
The correct approach is to remove it from the regression and run a new one.
Omitting the problematic predicter there is one more consideration concerning the removal of variables
from a model.
We can add 100 variables to a model and probably the predictive power of the model will be outstanding.
However this strategy makes regression analysis futile.
You are trying to use a few independent variables that approximately predict the result.
The tradeoff is complex but simplicity is better rewarded than higher explanatory power.
Finally the adjusted r squared is the basis for comparing regression models.
Once again it only makes sense to compare two models considering the same dependent variable and using
the same dataset.
If we compare two models that are about two dependent variables we will make an apples to oranges comparison.
If we use different data sets it's an apples to dinosaur's problem as you can see adjusted r squared
is a step in the right direction but should not be the only measure trusted.
Caution is advised.
Whereas thorough logic and diligence are mandatory in our next lesson.
We will learn how to assess the overall significance of a model.
Thanks for watching.