In the lecture about regression tables we mentioned the statistic which we saw in the Nova table.
Let's try to explain its essence and see how it's useful to us.
Much like the Z statistic that follows a normal distribution and the t statistic that follows the Student's
t distribution.
The F statistic follows an F distribution.
I'm calling it a statistic.
So it is used for tests right.
You guessed correctly the test is known as the test for overall significance of the model.
The null hypothesis is all the betas are equal to zero simultaneously.
The alternative hypothesis is at least one Bayda defers from zero.
What's the interpretation if all betas are zero then none of the independent variables matter.
Therefore our model has no merit.
Let's see the Nova table for the S.A.T. score college GPA regression.
The statistic is fifty five point five and its p value is zero point zero zero zero.
We say the overall model is significant.
Notice how the p value is a universal measure for all tests.
There is an F table used for the F statistic but we don't need it because the p value notion is so powerful
the F-test is important for multivariate regressions as it gives us some important insights.
Let's see the Nova table for the model where we added the random 1 to 3 variable that had nothing to
do with anything.
The statistic is twenty seven point eight and the p value is zero point zero zero zero.
You can see the f statistic is lower.
The model is still significant but less so the lower the statistic the closer to a non-significant model.
This is yet another tool that allows us to compare models OK.
This was the test for overall significance of the model.
Don't forget to look for the three zeros after the dot.
And thanks for watching.