OK great let's continue.
By introducing the concept of an estimator of a population parameter it is an approximation depending
solely on sample information a specific value is called an estimate.
There are two types of estimates point estimates and confidence interval estimates of point estimate
is a single number.
While a confidence interval naturally is an interval the two are closely related.
In fact the point estimate is located exactly in the middle of the confidence interval.
However confidence intervals provide much more information and are preferred when making inferences.
All right have we seen estimates so far.
Sure we have the sample mean X bar is a point estimate of the population mean mue.
Moreover the sample variance as squared was an estimate of the population variance Sigma squared.
There may be many estimators for the same variable.
However they all have two properties.
Bias and efficiency.
We will not prove them as the mathematics associated is out of the score of this course.
However you should have an idea about the concepts estimators are like judges.
We are always looking for the most efficient unbiased estimators an unbiased estimator has an expected
value equal to the population parameter.
Let's think of a biased estimator to explain that point.
What if somebody told you that you will have to find the average height of Americans by taking a sample
finding its mean and then adding one foot to that result.
So the formula is X bar plus 1 foot.
Well I hope you won't trust them.
They gave you an estimator but a biased one.
It makes much more sense that the average height of Americans is approximated just by the sample mean.
Right.
We say that the bias of this estimator is 1 foot clear.
OK great.
Let's move on to efficiency.
The most efficient estimators are the ones with the least variability of outcomes from the estimates
we know so far we haven't seen estimators with problematic variants.
So it is hard to exemplify.
It is enough to know that the most efficient means the unbiased estimator with the smallest variance.
All right in the next lecture we will explore confidence intervals.
So stick around.