High again in the previous lesson we learned about point estimators.
But as you can guess they are not very reliable.
Imagine visiting 5 percent of the restaurants in London and saying that the average meal is worth fifty
pounds.
You may be close but chances are that the true value is it really twenty two point fifty but somewhere
around it it's much safer to say that the average meal in London is somewhere between 20 and 25 pounds
isn't it.
In this way you have created a confidence interval around your point estimate of 20 2.50 a confidence
interval is a much more accurate representation of reality.
However there is still some uncertainty left which we measure in levels of confidence.
So getting back to our example you may say that you are 95 percent confident that the population parameter
lies between 20 and 25 quid.
Keep in mind that you can never be 100 percent confident unless you go through the entire population
and there is of course a 5 percent chance that the actual population parameter is outside of the 20
to 25 pounds range.
We'll observe that if the sample we have considered deviate significantly from the entire population.
All right.
There is one more ingredient needed.
The level of confidence it is denoted by one minus Alpha and is called the confidence level of the interval
Alpha is a value between 0 and 1.
For example if we want to be 95 percent confident that the parameter is inside the interval Alpha is
5 percent.
If we want a higher confidence level say 99 percent Alpha will be 1 percent.
Don't worry we will discuss this in more detail in our next video.
You can't wait until the next lesson.
Ok then here it is.
The formula for all confidence intervals is from the point estimate minus the reliability factor times
the standard error to the point estimate Plus the reliability factor times the standard error.
We know that the point estimate is values like X bar and S Bar right.
We also know what the standard error is one about the reliability factor.
We'll have to introduce in our next lesson.