A confidence interval is the range within which you expect the population parameter to be and its estimation
is based on the data we have in our sample.
There are two main situations when we can calculate the confidence intervals for a population when the
population variance is known and when it is unknown depending on which situation we are in we would
use a different calculation method.
In this lesson we will explore the confidence intervals for a population mean with a known variance
an important assumption and this calculation is that the population is normally distributed even if
it is not.
You should use a large sample and let the Central Limit Theorem do the normalization magic for you.
Remember if you work with a sample which is large enough you can assume normality of sample means Alright.
Let's say you want to become a data scientist and you are interested in the salary you're going to get.
You are also aware that population standard deviation of data science salaries is equal to fifteen thousand
dollars.
Furthermore you know the salaries are normally distributed and your sample consists of 30 salary's.
The formula for the confidence interval with a known variance is given below the population mean will
fall between the sample mean minus Z of Alpha divided by two times the standard error and the sample
mean plus Z of Alpha divided by two times the standard error the sample mean is the point estimator.
You know all about the standard error already.
So let's compute it using the formula.
What we have left is the so called reliability factor Z of Alpha divided by two Z is the statistic that
we've described earlier.
The standardized variable that has a standard normal distribution right.
And what about Alpha.
This is the same alpha we had when we defined our confidence level.
So for a confidence level of 95 percent Alpha would be equal to 5 percent.
Similarily for a confidence level of 99 percent Alpha would be equal to 1 percent.
It all falls into place.
Now let's get back to our example.
The sample mean is one hundred thousand two hundred dollars and the standard deviation is known to be
fifteen thousand dollars.
Thus the standard error is two thousand seven hundred thirty nine dollars.
Having calculated these values we can take the next step and choose our confidence level calm and confidence
levels are 90 percent 95 percent and 99 percent with respective Alfas of 10 percent 5 percent and 1
percent.
Another way to put in the value of alpha is 0.1 0.05 and 0.01 respectively.
Keep in mind that a 95 percent confidence interval means that you are sure that in 95 percent of the
cases the true population parameter would fall into the specified interval.
The CSY of Alpha comes from the so-called standard normal distribution table it is best to first see
it and then comment on it.
Let's say we want to find the values for the 95 percent confidence interval Alpha is 0.05.
Therefore we are looking for Z of Alpha divided by two or zero point zero to five in this table.
This will match the value of one minus zero point zero to five or zero point nine seventy five the corresponding
z comes from the sum of the row and column table headers associated with the cell.
In our case the value is one point nine plus 0.06 or 1.9 six.
A commonly used term for the z is critical value.
So we have found the critical value for this confidence interval.
Now we can easily substitute in the formula.
The final confidence interval becomes ninety four thousand eight hundred thirty three to one hundred
five thousand five hundred sixty eight.
The interpretation is the following.
We are 95 percent confident that the average data scientists salary will be in the interval.
Ninety four thousand eight hundred thirty three and one hundred five thousand five hundred sixty eight
dollars.
Let's repeat the exercise using a higher confidence level.
Say we want to be 99 percent certain of the outcome.
Alpha is zero point zero one.
We look at the table for the value of one minus 0.00 five which is equal to zero point nine nine five.
Bummer there is no such value.
When this happens we just have to round to the nearest value available the corresponding critical value
is 2.5 plus zero point zero or eight.
Thus 2.5 8 we plug it into our formula once more and the new confidence interval is equal to ninety
three thousand one hundred thirty five and one hundred seven thousand two hundred six.
This means that we are 99 percent confident that the average data scientists salary is going to lie
in the interval between ninety three thousand one hundred thirty five and one hundred seven thousand
two hundred six dollars.
Please note that in this case there is a tradeoff between the level of confidence we chose and the estimation
precision the interval we obtained is broader.
The opposite is also true.
A narrow confidence interval translate to higher uncertainty makes sense right.
If we are trying to estimate the population mean and we are picking a larger interval we are increasing
our chances of having an interval that actually includes the mean and vice versa.
If we want to be more specific about the population mean range.
This will take away from our confidence about this statement OK.
This lecture was a bit longer but very insightful.
Don't skip the exercises provided they will help you reinforce the knowledge about this concept which
is fundamental for everybody who wants to work with numbers in their job.
In the next few lessons we will study some particular cases and teach you how to find confidence intervals
for them.
Thanks for watching.