It's time for a short break from all these numbers and calculations I would like to tell you a story.
William Gosset was an English statistician who worked for the brewery of Guinness.
He developed different methods for the selection of the best yielding varieties of barley an important
ingredient when making beer Gosset found big samples tedious.
So he was trying to develop a way to extract small samples but still come up with meaningful predictions.
He was a curious and productive researcher and published a number of papers that are still relevant
today.
However due to the Guinness company policy he was not allowed to sign the papers with his own name.
Therefore all of his work was under the pen name student.
Later on a friend of his and a famous statistician Ronald Fischer stepping on the findings of Gosset
introduced the t statistic and the name that stuck with the corresponding distribution even today is
students t the Student's t distribution is one of the biggest breakthroughs in statistics as it allowed
inference through small samples with an unknown population variance.
This sitting can be applied to a big part of statistical problems we face today and is an important
part of this course.
All right visually the Student's t distribution looks much like a normal distribution but generally
has fatter tails fatter tails.
As you may remember allows for a higher dispersion of variables as there is more uncertainty in the
same way that the Z statistic is related to the standard normal distribution.
The statistic is related to the Student's t distribution.
The formula that allows us to calculate it is t with and minus 1 degrees of freedom any significance
level of Alpha equals the sample mean minus the population mean divided by the standard error of the
sample.
As you can see it is very similar to the Z statistic.
After all this is an approximation of the normal distribution.
The last characteristic of the Student's t statistic is that there are degrees of freedom.
Usually for a sample of N we have n minus 1 degrees of freedom.
So for a sample of 20 observations the degrees of freedom are 19.
Much like the standard normal distribution table.
We also have a students tea table.
Here it is.
The rows indicate different degrees of freedom.
Abbreviated as D F while the columns common Alfas.
Please note that after the 30th row the numbers don't vary that much.
Actually after 30 degrees of freedom the statistic table becomes almost the same as the Z statistic
as the degrees of freedom depend on the sample.
In essence the bigger the sample the closer we get to the actual numbers.
A common rule of thumb is that for a simple containing more than 50 observations we use the Z table
instead of the tea table.
All right great.
In our next lecture we will apply our knowledge.
In practice.