All right.
So we've learned that confidence intervals based on small samples from normally distributed populations
are calculated with the t statistic.
Let's revisit the example we saw earlier.
You are an aspiring did a scientist and are wondering how much the mean data scientists salary is you
have a sample of nine compensations you found on glass door and you have summarized the information
in the following table.
OK.
We've already calculated the sample mean and standard error which are ninety two thousand five hundred
thirty three dollars and four thousand six hundred forty four dollars respectively.
But this time we don't have one key piece of information.
The population variance.
No problem.
As the good statisticians that we are we will use the Student's t distribution.
Here's the formula that allows us to find a confidence interval for the mean of a population with an
unknown variance.
Let's compare it with the formula we used when the variance is known.
There are two key differences.
First instead of Z statistic we have a t statistic and second instead of population standard deviation
we have sample standard deviation.
Otherwise everything is the same so it shouldn't be that difficult to remember the logic behind constructing
confidence intervals.
In both cases is the same.
The only two inputs that change are the statistic at hand and the standard deviation when population
variance is known.
Population standard deviation goes with the Z statistic.
When population variance is unknown.
Several standard deviation goes with the t statistic.
All right so we have the sample mean standard deviation and sample size.
All we have to do is find the t statistic.
We will be able to obtain the t statistic from the tea table.
First we need to specify the degrees of freedom for the Student's t distribution.
There are n minus 1 degrees of freedom.
Our sample consists of nine observations.
So we have eight degrees of freedom.
Second we have to find Alpha divided by two.
Once again this depends on the confidence level that we want to obtain.
In this example we are going to use a confidence level of 95 percent.
This means that Alpha is equal to 5 percent.
Therefore half of Alpha would be 2.5 percent.
You can now see that the associated t statistic is 2.3 1 great.
Note that some tables you will find in books or online like this one have a C row.
The abbreviation stands for confidence interval.
Instead of finding Alpha we can just check the 95 percent confidence interval and get the same result.
Easy OK.
We have all the information needed so we just plug in the numbers.
What we get is a confidence interval from eighty one thousand eight hundred six dollars to one hundred
three thousand $261.
Let's compare this result to the result for the confidence interval with known population.
We got a 95 percent confidence interval that was between ninety four thousand eight hundred thirty three
dollars and one hundred five thousand five hundred sixty eight dollars.
You can clearly note that when we know the population variance we get a narrower confidence interval.
When we do not know the population variance there is a higher uncertainty that is reflected by wider
boundaries for our interval.
Makes sense doesn't it.
So what we learned today is that even when we do not know the population variance we can still make
predictions but they will be less accurate.
Furthermore the proper statistic for estimating the confidence interval when the population variance
is unknown is the t statistic and not the Z statistic.
All right great.
Thanks for watching.