Welcome back in the last few lessons we've been concentrating on confidence intervals.
We learned about two situations when the population variance is known which happens very rarely in practice
and when the variance is unknown and follows a Student's t distribution the goal of this lesson is less
about learning and more about clarifying alright.
These are the formulas that allow us to find confidence intervals as we noted in our previous lecture.
These parts are the ones that determine the span of the confidence interval.
There is a special name for these expressions.
Margin of error.
When the population variance is known the margin of error is equal to this expression and in the case
of population variance unknown the margin of error is equal to this expression instead.
So basically the confidence intervals could be summarized as follows.
The true population mean falls in the interval defined by the sample mean plus minus the margin of error.
Now we get to the core of this lesson.
Getting a smaller margin of error means that the confidence interval would be narrower as we want a
better prediction.
It is in our interest to have the narrowest possible confidence interval.
The best part is that we can actually control the margin of error.
Let's see its parts.
There is a statistic a stair deviation and the sample size the statistic and the standard deviation
are in the numerator so smaller statistic and smaller standard deviations will reduce the margin of
error.
How do we do that a higher level of confidence increases the statistic a higher statistic means a higher
margin of error.
This leads to a wider confidence interval.
Think about this example you took an exam and you want to make your prediction about the mean grade
obtained by all exam takers as a b c d and f are all possible grades.
We are 100 percent confident that the mean grade will be in the confidence interval from F to A.
Now if we lower the confidence level to 99 percent we may end up with a confidence interval from F plus
to a minus.
Remember the interpretation in 99 percent of the cases the population mean falls in the interval.
So with a 50 percent confidence level in 50 percent of the cases the true mean will fall in the specified
interval.
The only scenario under which this is possible is if the interval is narrower.
Therefore if the standard deviation and the sample size are kept constant a lower confidence level will
result in a narrower interval.
What about the standard deviation.
That's easy.
A lower standard deviation means that the dataset is more concentrated around the mean.
So we have a better chance to get it right.
For instance the mean grade in your class is B and you know that there were people with A's PC's DS
and a few F's.
How likely is it that you got a B.
Now compare this to a situation when the teacher said the mean of the class is around B and the lowest
grade is c..
In this case you are much more likely to get a B right in the first case the grades are dispersed while
in the second they are concentrated.
Lastly we have the sample size in the denominator higher sample sizes will decrease the margin of error.
This is also quite intuitive.
The more observations you have in your sample the more certain you are in the prediction.
This time you have a B plus there are 30 people in the class and you want to know if you performed above
the average you ask three of your friends and they all got A's.
Your sample of three people leads you to think you underperformed.
You get frustrated and start asking around some more the next 5 people you ask got Ds.
Now you have a sample of 8 people and it seems you did quite well.
After asking everyone in class the whole population that is you find out that the mean grade is B you
are above average by a small margin.
The conclusion is that the more observations there are in the sample the higher the chances of getting
a good idea about the true mean of the entire population.
All right.
Hopefully this clears up some doubts you may have had.
Thanks for watching.