Congratulations on reaching the last lesson of our regression analysis section.
Our focus here will be dummy variables apart from the offensive side of the word.
There is another meaning an imitation or a copy that stands as a substitute.
In regression analysis a dummy is a variable that is used to include categorical data into a regression
model.
So far we used only numerical data like the S.A.T. score and the GPA or the random 1 to 3 variable from
the adjusted R-squared.
Lesson.
Now we will explore how to include variables such as gender season and Brind into a regression we are
working with.
For instance let's take our GPA prediction example that we all know so very well generally.
Another good and suitable regress are for GPA is attendance.
Here is a data set that includes a variable that measures if a student attended more than 75 percent
of their university lecturers.
This is categorical data so we cannot simply put it in the regression our approach for this lesson will
be to go through the process of using a dummy and explain it later on.
OK here we go.
Let's include another column that is called Dummy attendance.
That is our dummy variable.
If the student attended more than 75 percent of the lessons the dummy will be equal to 1 otherwise it
will be a zero.
So we have transformed our Yes or no question into ones and zeros.
That's what the dummy name stands for.
We're imitating the categories with numbers.
All right.
I don't need the original attendance variable anymore as the dummy contains the same information.
Let's create a regression that explains the GPA with both S.A.T. scores and attendance.
The result is the following.
Our overall model is significant.
The SAT score is significant and the dummy is significant although barely So the adjusted R-squared
of this model is 0.4 to two which is an improvement from the 0.3 9:09 we got last time without attendance
that's not game changing but is still relevant.
The original model without the dummy variable was GPA equals zero point for eight plus 0.00 one five
times the S.A.T. score of a student.
The model including the dummy variable is GPA equals zero point eighty seven plus 0.00 1 3 times the
S.A.T. score of a student plus zero point 1 1 8 4 times the dummy.
Now we said that the dummy is 1 or 0.
So we can actually represent this equation with two others.
If the student did not attend the dummy will be zero.
So Zero Point 1 1 8 4 times 0 0.
The model becomes GPA equal seven plus 0.00 1 three times.
S.A. if the student attended the dummy will be one.
So the model becomes GPA equals zero point seven plus 0.00 1 3 times as 80 plus 0.1 1 8 for let's add
the intercept and the dummy together we get GPA equals zero point nine nine plus zero point zero zero
one three times S.A.T. graphically.
This looks in the following way.
So we have two models that have the same slope but they have a different intercept.
The students who attended are spread around the upper line.
On average their GPA is 0.1 one 8:4 higher than the GPA of students who did not attend
OK to use this model for prediction.
We need two pieces of information and S.A.T. score and the information whether a person attended more
than 75 percent of their lectures.
For example Joshua got hundred on his S.A.T. and did not attend 75 percent of his lessons.
Our model predicts that his graduation GPA will be three point zero eight Jennifer.
On the other hand got 670 on the S.A.T. but attended all of her lectures according to our regression.
She is expected to graduate with 3.1 6 as you can see although she scored lower on the S.A.T..
Her attendance turned things around for her.
Had we used our previous model with the dummy variable we would have predicted that Joshua would graduate
with three point zero or three and Jenny with 2.9 nine.
While Joshua's GPA barely changed we see a significant difference in the prediction about Jenny
OK this will do in our next lesson.
We will solve a practical example.
We will even use several dummy variables which will ensure you will reinforce what you've learned here.
See you next time.
And thanks for watching.