All right.
Now that we've covered the necessary theory it is time for some testing.
We are going to explore two types of tests drawn from a single population and drawn from multiple populations.
This is very similar to confidence intervals for a single population and confidence intervals for two
populations that we covered previously in the next few videos.
We all run tests for a single mean with both known variants and unknown variants.
Let's start with the test in which the variance is known.
Shall we for this test.
We will use our good old data scientist salary example.
Here's the data set one more time by now.
I hope you are able to calculate the sample mean.
It is one hundred thousand two hundred dollars.
The population variance is known and its standard deviation is equal to $15000.
Moreover the sample size is 30.
However you saw that according to Glassdoor the popular Salang information Web site the mean data scientists
Sellery is one hundred thirteen thousand dollars.
The sample that is available on glass door is based on self-reported numbers and you would like to see
if its value is correct.
We needed a two sided test as we were interested in knowing both if the celery is significantly less
than that or significantly more than that.
The null hypothesis is the population mean celery is one hundred thirteen thousand dollars.
We denote it as muse 0 equals one hundred thirteen thousand dollars.
The alternative hypothesis is that the population mean celery is different than one hundred thirteen
thousand dollars all right.
Formula time almost testing is done by standardizing the variable at hand and comparing it to the lower
case Z which follows a standard normal distribution.
Remember standardization we learned about it in the previous section.
Back then I told you it was very important and you will now see why.
For those that don't remember I suggest watching the video on sterilization once again for the others.
I will quickly go through it.
We standardize a variable by subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation.
Since it is a sample we use the standard error.
Thus the formula for standardization becomes capital Z is equal to the sample mean minus the value of
interest from the null hypothesis divided by the standard error.
In this way we obtain a distribution with a mean of zero.
Any standard deviation of one the upper case z should not be mistaken with the lowercase Z.
The uppercase Z is the standardized variable associated with the test and will be called the Z score.
From now on the lower case c is the one from the table that we talked about before and henceforth will
be referred to as the critical value all.
How does testing work.
Think about this.
The lowercase Z is normally distributed with a mean of 0.
Any standard deviation of 1.
The upper case C is normally distributed with a mean of X bar minus music Museo any standard deviation
of 1.
Standardization lets us compare the means.
The closer the difference of X bar amuse 0 to zero the closer the z score itself to zero this implies
a higher chance to accept the null hypothesis.
Let's go back to the example.
So what is the value of our standardized variable replug in the numbers that we have from the beginning
of the lesson.
What we get is a z score of minus 4.6 7.
Now we will compare the absolute value of minus 4.6 7 with a lower case Z of Alpha divided by 2 where
Alpha is the significance level.
Note that we use the absolute value as it is much easier to always compare positive capital Zee's with
positive lower cases.
Moreover some tables don't include negative values.
You should be aware that the two statements minus 4.6 seven is lower than the negative critical value
is the same as 4.6 7 is higher than the positive critical value.
Thus our decision rule becomes absolute value of the z score should be higher than the absolute value
of the critical value using 5 percent significance.
Our Alpha is 0.05.
Since it is a two sided test we check the table for Z of zero point zero to five the corresponding value
is 1.9 6.
The last thing we need to compare our standardized variable to is the critical value.
If the z score is higher than 1.9 6 we would reject the null hypothesis.
If it is lower we will accept it.
4.6 7 is higher than 1.9 6.
Therefore we reject the null hypothesis.
The answer is that at 5 percent significance level we have rejected the null hypothesis or at 5 percent
significance.
There is no statistical evidence that the mean salary is one hundred thirteen thousand dollars.
There are many other ways to express this and you will probably hear more about this later on in the
course what if we had a different significance level using 1 percent significance.
We have an alpha of zero point zero or one.
So Z of Alpha divided by 2 is 2.5 8.
Once again our z score a 4.6 7 is higher than 2.5 8 so we would reject the no hypothesis.
Even at the 1 percent significance.
But how much further can we go before we cannot reject the null hypothesis anymore.
Zero point five percent 0.1 percent.
There is a special technique that allows us to see what the significance of all is after which we will
be unable to reject the no hypothesis.
We will see in our next video.
Stay tuned.