Know we know how to test hypotheses and how to reject them.
Actually we rejected the hypothesis at various levels of significance but we couldn't find a level of
significance for which we could no longer do it.
This is the right moment to introduce a measure called the P-value.
This is the most common way to test hypotheses instead of testing at pre-assigned levels of significance.
We can find the smallest level of significance at which we can still reject the null hypothesis given
the observed sample statistic.
So how do we do that.
Recall the test with the data scientists salary.
We had a standard error of two thousand seven hundred thirty nine known population standard deviation
of 15000 normally distributed population and a sample size of 30 the corresponding z score was minus
4.6 7.
We rejected the hypothesis at significant levels of 0.05 and 0.01.
But we wanted to know how much lower we could go.
We can check the Z table for plus 4.6 7 which gives us the same result as minus 4.6 7 in most Z tables.
You would not find this value as it is so large.
Thus we round up to the Close's value available and get 0.00 0 1 way.
But how do we actually test the hypothesis.
Well after choosing a significance level of alpha you compare the P-value to it.
You should reject the hypothesis if the p value is lower than the significance level.
Therefore we can safely say that such a result is extremely significant by any measurement of significance.
Let's see another example if ours the score was 2.1 2 we would reject the no hypothesis at 5 percent
but not reject it at 1 percent significance.
Now it becomes more interesting at this point we can actually look at the table and then find the P-value
we look for the value that corresponds with 2.1 to and find that it is zero point 983 the p value for
a one sided test is 1 minus the number we see in the table.
So the corresponding p value is equal to zero point zero 1 7 the p value for a two sided test is 1 minus
the number we see in the table multiplied by 2.
Therefore the p value would be zero point zero three four.
This is also the answer to our question.
All right so where are the values used most testicle software packages run tests and then provide us
with a series of results one of them is P-value it is then up to the researcher to decide whether the
variable is statistically significant or not.
Generally software is designed to calculate the p value to the third digit after the separator.
The point is when you start conducting your own research you would love to be able to see the three
zeros after the dot.
The closer to 0 Your p value is the more significant is the result you've obtained.
The final consideration is that the p value is an extremely powerful measure as it works for all distributions
no matter if we are dealing with the normal Student's t by Gnomeo or uniform distribution.
Whatever the test the P-value rationale holds if the p value is lower than the level of significance
you reject the null hypothesis.
Having said that you would normally use the p value in the presence of a digital medium throughout this
course.
I recommend that you use online P-value calculators to support your studies and double check your answers
when doing exercises.
Please download the PTF that comes with this lesson as it will include detailed instructions for how
to use online P-value calculators.