All right.
Great.
Now that we know what the value is and how to use it we will give back to hypothesis testing.
We saw only one of the two possible cases.
Remember we haven't covered the more commonly observed case when the population variance is unknown.
All right.
Imagine you are the marketing analyst of a company and you've been asked to estimate if the e-mail open
rate of one of the firm's competitors is above your company's.
Your company has an open rate of 40 percent an email open rate is a measure of how many people on the
e-mail list actually open the e-mails they have received.
At first you struggled to figure out how to get such specific information about a competitor company
but then you see that an employee of that competitor company posted a selfie on Facebook saying oh well
the e-mail management software we are using drives me nuts in the background.
You can see her screen and it shows clearly the summaries of the last 10 email campaigns that were sent
and their corresponding open rates.
Bingo with your statistical skills.
That's all you need a little help from Facebook.
Let's stay the hypotheses no hypothesis mean open rate is lower or equal to 40 percent.
Alternative Hypothesis mean open rate is higher than 40 percent.
No.
That in hypothesis testing we are aiming to reject the no hypothesis when we want to test if the open
rate is higher than 40 percent.
The null hypothesis actually states the opposite statement.
Also pay attention that this time we're dealing with a one sided test.
All right.
Your boss told you that 0.05 is an adequate significance level for this test.
So that's what you'll use.
Here's the data set you calculate the sample mean and get thirty seven point seven percent.
The sample standard deviation is thirteen point seventy four percent.
Thus the standard error is 1.3 7 percent.
You assume that the population of open rates of sent e-mails is normally distributed like confidence
intervals with variants are known and a small sample.
The correct statistic to use is the t statistic.
Remember you do not know the variance and the sample is not big enough.
This means that the variable follows the Student's t distribution and you must employ the t statistic
let's calculate it then we calculate the T score the same way as the Z score the T score is equal to
the sample mean minus the hypothesized mean value divided by the standard error.
The result that we get is minus 1.6 7 as we said earlier is easier to work with positive numbers so
we should compare the absolute value of minus 1.6 7 with the appropriate t with and minus 1 degrees
of freedom at 0.05 one sided significance.
We quickly navigate through the table and get 1.8 three at the 5 percent significance critical value
OK 1.6 7 is lower than 1.8 3.
Remember the decision rule.
If the absolute value of the T score is lower than the statistic from the table we cannot reject the
no hypothesis.
Therefore we must accept it.
What you do next is you go and tell your boss that at this level of significance statistically we cannot
say that the evil open rate of our competitors is higher than 40 percent.
What about the second measurement we saw.
What was that.
Ah yes the p value the p value of this statistic is 0.06 5 as the p value is greater than the significance
level of 0.05.
We come to the same conclusion.
We cannot reject the null hypothesis.
Let's do a quick check if the significance level was zero point zero or one the p value would still
be higher and we wouldn't reject the null hypothesis.
This is an important observation that we haven't noted before.
If we cannot reject a test at 0.05 significance we cannot reject it at smaller levels either.
All right that's all for now.
Make sure you learn the material by doing the exercises.
After this lesson.
Thanks for watching.