We are not done with Hypothesis Testing just yet remember how we started with confidence intervals for
a single population mean and then switched to examples considering multiple populations.
While we are in the same situation here single populations are just the beginning time to do multiple
means.
We will start with dependent samples.
The most intuitive examples of dependent samples are the ones you have been through like weight loss
and blood tests.
The sample is drawn from Weight-Loss data or concentration of nutrient data.
But the subject of interest is the same person before and after OK let's get to work.
Do you recall our example with the magnesium levels in one's blood.
There was this drug company developing a new pill that supposably increased levels of magnesium of recipients.
There were 10 people involved in the study that were taking the drug for some time and we calculated
confidence intervals that helped us study the effects of that drug.
They indicated the range of plausible values for the population mean.
This time we want to come to a single definite conclusion about the effectiveness of the drug.
All right.
Let's state the no hypothesis.
The population mean before is greater or equal than the population mean after the alternative is that
the population mean before is lower than the one after.
Once again we want to know if the magnesium levels are higher.
We construct a no and alternative hypotheses in such a way so that we are aiming to reject the null
hypothesis.
OK let's reorder a bit.
Age 0 is myu before which is equal or higher than mu after this is equivalent to MMU before minus myu
after is equal to zero or positive.
We can substitute this with capital D 0 it stands for the hypothesized population mean difference.
So we restate our hypotheses using d for simplicity.
Now we have our test designed.
Let's crunch some numbers.
Here's the data set.
We have 10 observations people have registered before and after.
Naturally the difference is equal to before minus after we can calculate the sample mean of the difference
we get minus 0.3 3.
The sample standard deviation is zero point four or five.
And the standard error is 0.1 for the appropriate statistic to use here is the t statistic.
We have a small sample.
We assume normal distribution of the population and we don't know the variance.
So the score is equal to the following expression.
Now we can simply carry up the calculations and find that its value is minus 2.2 none since we don't
want to choose a level of significance.
Well solve the problem with the P-value in order to find the value of this one sided test.
We may go to the table and see it is somewhere between zero point zero one and zero point zero to five.
As I told you earlier using software is much easier.
So after using an online P-value calculator I can tell you that it is exactly zero point zero to four.
What was that decision rule again.
If the p value is lower than the significance level we are interested in.
We reject the no hypothesis.
OK so if the level of significance is 0.05 and the p value is lower we will be able to reject the hypothesis
at 5 percent if the level of significance is zero point zero one however the p value is higher.
So we cannot reject the no hypothesis at a 1 percent level of significance.
The lowest value for which we can reject it is zero point zero to four which is exactly the p value.
What does this tell us.
Well it is up to the researcher to choose the level of significance in the case of the magnesium pill.
We expect that the researcher will be very cautious as he would want to know if this is an effective
pill they will be able to actually help people.
If we cannot say that the pill works at a 1 percent significance level perhaps it is better to take
it back to the laboratory and alternative would be to test again and increase the sample size for better
results.
A sample of 100 people would improve the level of precision significantly.
All right so we've done some more hypothesis testing and we've explored some factors that help you determine
the significance level of the test.
Stay with us for our next lesson where we will learn how to test independent samples.