High again as you probably expected in this lesson we will learn about independent samples with known
variants.
Once get into the example you may remember this one we are about to test the average grades of students
from two departments in a UK university.
I would like to remind you that in the UK grades are expressed in percentages.
The two departments are engineering and management.
We were told by the Dean that engineering is a tougher discipline and people tend to get lower grades.
He believes that on average management students outperform engineering students by four percentage points.
Now it is our job to verify if that is the case.
Let's state the two hypotheses age zero is the difference between the means of the two populations is
for or stated differently.
New engineering minus new management is equal to minus four.
H1 is the population mean.
Difference is different than minus for.
Once again this is a two sided test.
Our research question is not to find the difference but to check if it is exactly the minus for right.
Let's get our hands dirty.
Here's the table that summarizes the data.
The sample sizes are 170 respectively.
The sample means are 58 percent and 65 percent and the population standard deviations are 10 percent
and 6 percent and are known from the past data.
If you remember when the population is known for independent samples the standard error of the difference
is equal to the square root of the sum of the variance of engineering divided by its simple size and
the variance of management.
Again divided by sample size.
All we have left is to compute the test autistic.
We have big samples and known variances.
Therefore we can use the Z statistic.
I hope you are getting the point.
Small samples and unknown variances mean t.
When we have large samples and unknown variances.
It is up to the researcher but generally it is OK to use z in that case as well.
All right here's the formula for the test stick cystic sample difference mean minus hypothesized difference
mean divided by the standard error.
We plug in the numbers and get a z score of minus 2.4 for let's calculate the p value once again I'll
just tell you the p value.
As usually you will obtain it using a software.
The p value of the two sided test is 0.01 5.
We can say at 5 percent significance which is common for such a study.
The p value of zero point zero 1 5 is lower than 0.05.
Thus we reject the null hypothesis.
There is enough statistical evidence that the difference of the two means is not 4 percent.
Alright cool.
Here's a trick What if you want to know if the difference is higher or lower than for the sign of the
test tested mistake can give you that information.
A minus sign of the tested tested means it's smaller if you reverse engineered the standardization process
you will find that the true value is likely to be lower than the hypothesized value.
In our case this translates into the true mean is likely to be lower than minus for lower than minus
for entails that possible values are minus 5 minus 6 and so on.
This is additional information you can give to the Dean.
All right.
Done with that lesson too.
Let's proceed to the final topic.
Independent samples and unknown variances.