This is the final lesson we'll do on testing.
The last case we'll examine is the one with independent samples and unknown variances which are assumed
to be equal.
I'll quickly brush up your memory on the data set we did in the confidence interval section.
You were trying to see if apples in New York are as expensive as the ones in L.A. You went to 10 grocery
shops in New York and your friend Paul who lives in L.A. went to eight grocery shops there you got all
the prices and put them in a table.
You didn't know the population variance of the Apple prices but you assumed it should be the same for
New York and L.A. red state the no and alternative hypotheses age zero myu in NY is equal to you in
L.A. or myu and y minus myu L.A. is equal to zero.
H-1 new in NY differs from you in L.A. or me and why minus L.A. differs from zero.
All right.
That's our data set.
We have also calculated the sample means standard deviations and sample sizes what can we do when the
variance is unknown but assumed to be equal.
Earlier we used the pooled variance formula.
Well here it is again.
Remember all right it's all about plugging in numbers.
So I'll save you the trouble.
The pooled variance is 0.05.
One last thing we need is the standard error of the difference of means it is given by the following
formula.
I am going faster than usual as we have seen all of this before.
Moreover testing is about understanding computation is routine.
So let's start testing shall we small samples variance unknown.
Which statistic do we need exactly.
It's the statistic again.
How many degrees of freedom.
You may recall it from earlier it was the combined sample size minus the number of variables.
So 10 plus eight minus two which gives a 16.
Let's see the t statistic formula.
Once again the difference between simple means minus the difference between hypothesized true means
divided by the standard error after plugging in everything we get a tested mistake of 6.5 3.
Do we need to compare it.
This is by far the most extreme testing stick we have seen.
You will have a hard time finding it in the table for common tests.
A rule of thumb is to reject the null hypothesis when the score is bigger than 2.
Generally for z score and score a value higher than 4 is extremely significant.
Let's see the two sided P-value the p value of this test is lower than 0.00 0 somewhere around zero
point 0 0 0 0 0 1.
In our lesson about p value we said researchers are always looking for those three zeros after the dot.
It means the test is extremely significant and the probability of making a type 1 error is virtually
zero.
Therefore we reject the null hypothesis at all common and uncommon levels of significance.
There is strong statistical evidence that the price of apples in New York differs from an L.A. but such
an extreme result may also mean the hypothesis is pointless or poorly designed from the mean values
of 3.9 four and three point to five.
And with such small and closed standard deviations of around 0.2 we could easily say the prices are
different.
No testing needed.
A much more interesting question would be if the price of apples in New York is 20 percent higher than
in L.A..
I will leave you this exercise for homework.
All right.
We're done with hypothesis testing.
Cheers and thanks for watching.